<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of advice to a young gentleman of an honourable family, now in his travels beyond the seas for his more safe and profitable conduct in the three great instances, of study, moral deportment, and religion : in three parts / by a True son of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>True son of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11802008</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11802008</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49390</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48116)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49390)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 540:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of advice to a young gentleman of an honourable family, now in his travels beyond the seas for his more safe and profitable conduct in the three great instances, of study, moral deportment, and religion : in three parts / by a True son of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>True son of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Young men --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF ADVICE TO A YOUNG GENTLEMAN Of an Honourable FAMILY, Now in His TRAVELS Beyond the SEA'S: For his more ſafe and profitable Conduct in the Three great Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of <hi>Study, Moral Deportment,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> In Three Parts. By a True Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Clavell,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Peacock</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>July</hi> 25th. 1688.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Old Diſtemper returning ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly upon me, I could not wait on you as I deſign'd, and ſee you on Ship-board: Yet my hearty Prayers and Well-wiſhes have, and ſhall ever attend you, for the good Succeſs of your Travels, and ſafe Return. I think my ſelf alſo obliged to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late your happy Voyage, and hopeful Settlement (and as I am informed) in a flouriſhing and well-govern'd <hi>Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> where you cannot want Means and Opportunities to improve your Parts conſiderably, and enrich your Soul with ſuch excellent Habits, as none of your Rank and Years may out-do you in the moſt deſirable Accompliſhments of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Wiſdom and Experience.</p>
            <p>But (Sir,) beſides thoſe many Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations which I ſhall always recognize with the greateſt Expreſſions of Love and Gratitude, I have ſeveral other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb facs="tcp:49390:3"/>and Inducements, (as you'll ſee in the Sequel of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi>) which have prompted me to give you the trouble of peruſing theſe following <hi>Sheets:</hi> And tho I am very ſenſible, that you cannot want the <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> of Men far more eminent for <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> than I durſt ever pretend to; yet my Endeavours may have their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Influence (and kind Acceptance) as the Effect of undiſſembled Love and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, and the Product of his retired and ſerious Thoughts, who (to his power) ever was, is, and, God willing, ſhall be a true Friend to your Self and Family.</p>
            <p>Yet I muſt beg leave to tell you, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I proceed to the ſubject Matter of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi>) that the Eyes of your <hi>Country</hi> are much upon you, as the hopeful <hi>Son</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Father;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt expect, as your Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo your Defects will be narrowly and critically obſerved. You muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either ſtudy to equal, and (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) out-do his eminent <hi>Vertues</hi> and <hi>Endowments,</hi> or otherwiſe you'll find that they'll exceedingly leſſen and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe
<pb facs="tcp:49390:3"/>your own. Beſides, you have left your Country, Relations and Friends, for the increaſe of Learning and Experience; we do all therefore hope to ſee the generous and worthy Fruits and Effects of your Care and Induſtry, and as great a change in your <hi>Perſon</hi> as in the <hi>Climate.</hi> Nor can it be much ſatisfaction to your ſelf or others, tho you be able to give an account (at your return) of the ſtrange <hi>Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Event:</hi> For, the Fruits of <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Travel</hi> ſhould not reſt there, but your chief buſineſs will be to culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and beautifie your Soul with ſuch uſeful and profitable Knowledge, as may be a future benefit both to your ſelf and others; nor can any thing leſs than this, counter vail the great Charge, Hazzards, and Fatigues of <hi>Travel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſhould alſo conſider (Sir,) that your Co-temporaries here are growing up apace, and may be great <hi>Proficients</hi> in all ſorts of Learning; and therefore as you'll have greater Opportunities, ſo you muſt endeavour to make a ſutable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in all the gentiel, ingenuous and vertuous Accompliſhments, both of
<pb facs="tcp:49390:4"/>Mind and Body. But if by their Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence they ſhould out-ſtrip you, it would be no little Reflection; not to mention the fruitleſs expence of Time and Money, and the far greater Hazzards you run upon amongſt <hi>Foreigners</hi> and <hi>Fugitives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will it be unſeaſonable to remark to you, that ſeveral <hi>Young Gentlemen</hi> (within the compaſs of your own obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,) have returned from beyond <hi>Sea's,</hi> as ignorant to the full, and more immoral and extravagant, than if they had never left the Smoak of their own Chimneys. They have indeed dearly purchaſed, and brought over with them ſome new <hi>Modes,</hi> affected <hi>Geſtures,</hi> (if not the Diſeaſes of the Country,) and ſuch Language and Deportment as are not only ungentiel and unbecoming, but unmanly and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: (We ſhall have occaſion to take notice of ſome <hi>Particulars</hi> afterwards;) inſomuch that they are ſo far from being either wiſer, or better for their <hi>Travels,</hi> that (to give them their due) they have only commenced <hi>Maſters</hi> of that <hi>helliſh</hi> and <hi>black Art</hi> of <hi>Debauchery, Irreligion</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs.</hi> But,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:4"/>
            <p>Theſe Examples (Sir,) are only noted by way of <hi>caution:</hi> For we know, and ſhall always hope for, and expect better Things and Fruits from you: And your virtuous <hi>Temper,</hi> and hither to religious <hi>Education,</hi> will be a Sovereign <hi>Antidote,</hi> and ſure <hi>Defenſitive</hi> againſt all the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and charming <hi>Illectives</hi> you can poſſibly meet with. To which give me leave to add the following <hi>Advice,</hi> which I hope may be uſeful to you in all your <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels;</hi> nor ſhall it be unſeaſonable, whilſt you continue in that well govern'd <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> where perhaps the leaſt Danger is neither fear'd nor ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you with a longer <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordium:</hi> What I have further to impart, ſhall for Methods ſake, be comprehended under theſe <hi>Three</hi> following <hi>Heads of Diſcourſe.</hi> And the</p>
            <p>Firſt, will reſpect the well-husbanding and management of your <hi>Time</hi> in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your <hi>Studies,</hi> or <hi>Converſation</hi> with others. The</p>
            <p>Second, <hi>Your Morals,</hi> and <hi>Civil De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment.</hi> And the</p>
            <p>Third, <hi>Your Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49390:5"/>
            <p>In all which I ſhall endeavour to lay down ſuch <hi>Rules,</hi> as I hope may direct and encourage you to imploy your <hi>Time</hi> to the beſt Purpoſes; ſo that you may go on chearfully in your <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> with the greateſt ſucceſs, delight and ſatisfaction; and return home thro' Gods Bleſſing, every way accompliſht, as a well-bred <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> a good <hi>Scholar,</hi> and a ſound <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi> All which would be the greateſt Comfort and Bleſſing to your <hi>Parents,</hi> an Ornament to your <hi>Country,</hi> and the moſt peculiar Happineſs to your <hi>Self.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Of theſe ſeverally and in Order. And Firſt,</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="travel_advice_manual">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49390:5"/>
               <head>A LETTER OF ADVICE TO A YOUNG GENTLEMAN Now in His TRAVELS Beyond the SEA'S, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> PART I. <hi>Of ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DIES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOW (Sir) it would be an ill and unaccountable Application of your <hi>Time,</hi> if your <hi>Quality</hi> (as we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49390:6"/>have ſeen in too many) ſhould make you impatient of Diſcipline and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, or make you conſult your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Eaſe; the Effects whereof are uſually dangerous and deſtructive. For ſince God has bleſſed and ennobled you with the Priviledges of Birth and Blood, and an ingenuous and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Education, you ſhould imploy your Time and Faculties in the ſearch of, and purſuit after thoſe things which now, and in the after-courſe of your Life, will afford you the greateſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, as well as Pleaſure and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. You muſt not fancy then, that God made you only for Sports and Paſtimes, but gentiel and heroic Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes: Let thoſe who underſtand no better, pleaſe and divert themſelves with their Horſes, Dogs, Wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But what are all theſe to the more noble and worthy Endowments of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and a Scholar? And ſeeing God has been pleaſed to bleſs you with the underſtanding and all other Faculties of a Man (and thoſe too in the beſt degree) imploy the moſt conſiderable part of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49390:6"/>your Time (eſpecially now whilſt you have Leiſure, Opportunity, and few Avocations) at your <hi>Book,</hi> and in your <hi>Study.</hi> For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, As this will adorn your Soul with the greateſt Treaſures this World can afford, ſo you'l have cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate to your ſelf your own Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and God Almighty will bleſs and proſper you in your Endeavours: Who even in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Pleaſure to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> (tho certainly as Noble as any of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendents) without Labour and Induſtry. Nor can your retired and ſeeming Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity in your <hi>Studies</hi> leſſen your Gentility, ſince there's no well-bred <hi>Scholar</hi> that can fail of the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Character of a Gentleman. But beſides,</p>
               <p>Secondly, You'l hereby become not only more courteous and obliging to all you converſe with, but more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable alſo of managing (with Prudence and Diſcretion) thoſe weighty Affairs which may await you at your Return; and your Birth and Education will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49390:7"/>you to, both of Juſtice and State. Beſides, you'l better underſtand what Reſpect and Encouragement is defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly due to Learned Men, (ſuch I mean as are diligent, ſober and pious) and herein your dear and worthy <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> may be a Pattern to you, who by his diſcreet and obliging Carriage, has extreamly endear'd himſelf to all Scholars, but the Orthodox Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> eſpecially. And hence 'tis very obſervable, that thoſe Gentlemen only who have purchaſed to themſelves the honour of Learning and true Breeding, know beſt how to value and eſteem, and are moſt willing to encourage thoſe Attainments in others; which will alſo have a mighty Influence upon all your Dependents, as well as others below you, who do uſually ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect or contemn wiſe and good Men, by the Examples of their <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Conſider,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That whereas the Vertues or Vices of private Men do common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſs without much Notice or Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you'l beſet as it were a <hi>Beacon</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49390:7"/>an Hill; and as the Words of great Men are uſually <hi>Maxims</hi> and <hi>Theorems,</hi> ſo their Actions become Examples, Rules and Preſidents for others to ſteer and walk by. Beſides, you'l be no leſs eſteemed and admired for the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of your natural and acquired Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, than herein for the ſway and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of your Authority; nor can any thing be more baſe and inglorious, than a Gentleman only by name, whoſe Soul is ignorant and Life immoral.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There's nothing in this World, which can countervail the great Expence of your Time and Pains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> (as before) which are only attainable by <hi>Study</hi> and a ſutable <hi>Converſation</hi> with Scholars and Men of Parts; for hereby you may be qualified both for Action and Speculation, and excel the <hi>Mobile</hi> as much in Underſtanding and Vertue, as Nobility of Birth and gentiel Extraction. Now, theſe are the genuine and proper Fruits of <hi>Education and Study;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you imploy and improve your Time and Faculties to theſe purpoſes, tho per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49390:8"/>you may gratifie and pleaſe your Fancy with vain and empty Delights, yet your Underſtanding will prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful; and after many tedious and dangerous <hi>Traverſes,</hi> you may return Home with a ſhatter'd Body, and a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and empty Soul.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all ſuch generous <hi>Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as will prevail with your ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Temper and Inclination, to keep cloſe to your <hi>Studies:</hi> But as a further Obligation and Inforcement, give me leave to remind you of the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of ſome (who would neither be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to love Learning nor Books) which may be a ſure <hi>Caution</hi> to you to avoid thoſe Sins and Indiſcretions of licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ungovern'd Youth.</p>
               <p>For alaſs! we have many deplorable Inſtances (the Sparks and Blades of our Age) who conſume their Time, Parts, Wit, Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in purſuit of the greateſt Fooleries and Vanities in the World, to the greateſt ſhame and diſgrace of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſcandal of others; as if they were a diſtinct <hi>Species</hi> from all Rational Beings, and made only for a Sword, or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49390:8"/>a Horſe, or a Dog, and the other brutiſh and ſenſual Exerciſes of Luxury and Profaneneſs. I am no Enemy to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and innocent Pleaſures; but thoſe <hi>Sots</hi> and <hi>Ignaro's</hi> make it their Trade and way of Living, to obſerve all Modes and Faſhions, drink, ſwear, curſe, whore, game, ſight and quarrel like Hectors and Madmen, deſpiſe and ſcorn all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and run on in a full Carreer of Sin and Extravagance.</p>
               <p>Inſomuch, that I'm afraid they have ſcarce leiſure to ſay their Prayers, or look on a Book, and therefore wholly unfit for Chriſtian or ingenuous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; (their Dogs, Horſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being uſually the Subjects of their <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> in their more ſerious Intervals). By all which inhuman Methods, many of them are become ſo barbarouſly Ignorant, and void of all Learning, that they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgot that ever they were at <hi>Schools</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> (unleſs they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to remember ſome <hi>Pranks</hi> they play'd there) and are as much ſtrangers to <hi>Humanity, Philoſophy, Hiſtory, &amp;c.</hi> as if there had been never any ſuch thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49390:9"/>as Books or Learning in the World.</p>
               <p>Nor are theſe the Faults only of our home-bred Gentlemen; (for we have many learned, wiſe, and good Men, who never had the Curioſity nor Convenience of Travel) but even of thoſe who have ſeen many Foreign Countries, Cities, Delights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet neglecting the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they went about (as we have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved already) have returned home after many impertinent Wandrings, more vain and prodigal, wicked and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, than thoſe Companions of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Epicuriſm they left behind them. For what pleaſure and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has that Man, who has ſeen all the Novelties and Curioſities in the World, if he has ſtudied nothing elſe but to pleaſe and pamper his own Appetite? All that we can ſay of him, is, that he has beſtowed much pains to no purpoſe, or for that which is worſe; and bought his Sins and Vanities at a dearer rate than others.</p>
               <p>Thus, I have ſet before you thoſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> and <hi>Motives,</hi> and <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Hazards,</hi> on the right hand and on the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49390:9"/>left, which your <hi>Prudence</hi> will conſider betimes; ſo, that you may improve all thoſe Opportunities that fall in your way to the beſt advantages, leſt you ſhould unhappily <hi>miſcarry</hi> in your great <hi>Adventure,</hi> (as thoſe miſerable Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we have already noted; which the Lord of his great mercy avert.</p>
               <p>Conſider again, that your Station, Quality and Parts, may diſpoſe you at your Return for Offices of Honour and Truſt; wherein you may be highly Serviceable to your King and Country, as your <hi>worthy Father</hi> is, and has been before you: Nor can any <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> be duly qualified to adminiſter Juſtice or Counſel, with eaſe and ſatisfaction to himſelf, or for the benefit of others, but by ſuch habitual Accompliſhments as are the proper Reſults of <hi>Study</hi> and <hi>Obſervation:</hi> Inſomuch that <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> Emperour, did ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>That he had rather abound in Knowledge than Riches and Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides thoſe foregoing <hi>Topicks,</hi> you'l find by <hi>Experience,</hi> that the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as well as the Benefits of <hi>Study,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49390:10"/>are ſo charming and delightful, that 'tis next to impoſſible for a <hi>Scholar</hi> to be idle: Eſpecially conſidering (as a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man obſerves) the many Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Reaſon, the ſweetneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of Knowledge, the great range and multitude of Thoughts and Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; for there's much wit in Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in Philoſophy Reaſon, improved, in Mathematicks Acuteneſs, in Hiſtory curious and ſtrange Events, in Politicks variety of Projects and Deſigns, in Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſweet and delightful Eloquence, in Divinity ſupernatural Light, Rules of holy Living and Dying, and heavenly Devotions: Which laſt will be a means to ſanctifie all Endeavours to your uſe, and make all your other <hi>Studies</hi> both pleaſant and profitable.</p>
               <p>Now a ſtrict and diligent Enquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all theſe ſeveral ſorts of Learning, will fill up all the empty Spaces of your <hi>Time,</hi> which is commonly miſ-imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if not vainly miſ-ſpent, by all thoſe Gentlemen that are not Scholars. You may alter the <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Courſe</hi> of your <hi>Studies</hi> as you pleaſe, ſo that there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49390:10"/>ſhall never be any ſpare Time upon your hands; nor will it ever ſeem to paſs away ſlowly. But ſeeing the <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of Time well,</hi> is a thing of the greateſt advantage and importance to a <hi>Student;</hi> I ſhall give you an account of the <hi>Method</hi> which I have uſed, and found very ſucceſsful in the Conduct of mine own <hi>Studies:</hi> Yet I would not have you to obſerve it ſo exactly, as to neglect the more ſeaſonable <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> of others.</p>
               <p>Now I have always thought, that 'tis the Duty and Intereſt of every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to be well skill'd in the divine Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick of numbring his Days: For Time is a precious Jewel, for which we muſt all be accountable; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he who loſes a Day is dangerouſly prodigal; but thoſe that dare miſ-ſpend it, little leſs than deſperate. For the prevention then of thoſe Evils and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs reſulting from the fruitleſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of <hi>Time,</hi> I ſhall propound to you this following <hi>Method.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Riſe early in the Morning, if your Health permit; for <hi>Aurora muſis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49390:11"/>amica,</hi> and the ſooner the more early the Bleſſing. Let your <hi>firſt Thoughts</hi> be always with <hi>God;</hi> return him moſt humble and hearty <hi>Thanks</hi> for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment and Protection from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the Night. Preſent the <hi>firſt Fruits</hi> of your Reaſon and other Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to your <hi>Maker;</hi> think on him whilſt you are dreſſing, and humbly beg that you may be clothed upon with the Robes of your Saviours Righteouſneſs, and the moſt precious Ornaments of his Grace and Spirit.</p>
               <p>Then return to your <hi>Cloſet,</hi> and pray earneſtly, ſervently, conſtantly, devoutly and affectionately unto God, for your Preſervation that day, and for ever, from Temptation. Sin and Danger; and that he would ſanctifie your Perſon, and bleſs and proſper you in your <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi> 'Twas <hi>Luthers</hi> obſervation of himſelf, that <hi>bene or aſſe eſt bene ſtuduiſſe;</hi> and if your Heart be early ſeaſon'd with Gods Preſence, 'twill reliſh of him all the day after. And when you have thus happily performed your <hi>Morning Devotions,</hi> then,</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49390:11"/>
               <p>Secondly, Sit down a little and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider (eſpecially if you have occaſion to go abroad or entertain Company that day at your Chamber,) what Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Sins you are in danger to run upon; reſolve againſt them, and ſee that your Purpoſes be fixt and ſteady: So that if any of thoſe Temptations ſhould afterwards aſſault you, call to mind what you have reſolved on in your <hi>Cloſet,</hi> and then endeavour to arm your ſelf againſt them with the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your Religion; as the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of <hi>Death, Judgment, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi> But if you expect nothing <hi>extraordinary</hi> that day, (intending to continue in the courſe of your <hi>Studies,</hi>) then a ſerious Recommendation of your Perſon and Aſſairs to God, in a general <hi>Petition,</hi> will be acceptable and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Begin your <hi>Studies</hi> with reading a <hi>Chapter</hi> or more of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> every <hi>morning,</hi> till you have read it all over; and then begin again; always obſerving the ſame <hi>Method.</hi> Meditate of, and conſider well what
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49390:12"/>you read, that you may thence collect ſome uſeful <hi>Notes</hi> and <hi>Obſervations,</hi> for the Confirmation of your Faith, and Conduct of your Manners in the ways of Religion. And having read ſome Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Holy Scripture ſeriouſly and deliberately, (for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it, you may conſult Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi> Paraphraſe, or <hi>Grotius;</hi>) this, with your Prayers, will prepare you for your other <hi>Studies.</hi> Wherein,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Your <hi>Tutor</hi> will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to give you the moſt proper and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>Advice.</hi> Your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will be chiefly (as I ſuppoſe) <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicks</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy:</hi> Now if you'l but take pains to be an accurate <hi>Logician,</hi> and thorow-paced <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> (which will not require very much time, if you be always careful to attend the Lectures and Diſputations in the <hi>Schools</hi>) you'l readily underſtand any Author; and the whole courſe of all your future <hi>Studies,</hi> will not only thereby become beneficial, but pleaſant and delightful.</p>
               <p>Yet herein I deſire to <hi>caution</hi> you, not to ſpend too much <hi>Time</hi> in dry and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49390:12"/>uſeleſs <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Speculations,</hi> being a Fault which I have obſerved in the Methods of reading <hi>Philoſophy</hi> in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities;</hi> for no <hi>Study</hi> is worth a Mans while that's not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Profit, and ſuch unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Reaſons and Arguments as are in a great meaſure able to ſilence all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Debates, ſeeing the capacity of the Ignorant lyes as much below ſuch <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Curioſities,</hi> as the more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and judicious are above them; ſo that there remains to all in things du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious and only probable, a Power to admit, or reject what Opinions they pleaſe. Therefore I would recommend <hi>Mathematicks</hi> next to <hi>Logicks,</hi> as the moſt uſeful part of <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> for this <hi>Science</hi> propoſes nothing but what's apparent by moſt undeniable <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations;</hi> which Knowledge is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the chief we can acquire upon Earth, but will alſo accompany us to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, When you have leiſure, read over your <hi>Claſſick Authors,</hi> and remark with your Pen what you find moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in them; for as you'l hereby
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49390:13"/>underſtand the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of the moſt antient and celebrated <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens;</hi> ſo this ſort of Learning will qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie you to write and ſpeak Latin well: And when you have obtained this <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,</hi> you cannot be a ſtranger in any place where you come; nor can any thing be a greater Ornament to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman and a Scholar.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, And ſeeing your Quality and Eſtate will exempt you from all other Profeſſions but that of a <hi>States-man,</hi> the Knowledge of all ſorts of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> will be very uſeful and neceſſary; but eſpecially <hi>French Authors,</hi> being of all others the moſt accurate in <hi>Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Memoirs,</hi> recorded by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and publiſht by their <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries</hi> after their Deaths: For 'tis obſerv'd by a Perſon of great Judgment and Policy, that none make more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Reports</hi> of things done in all Nations than <hi>Ambaſſadours;</hi> having the beſt and moſt authentick Intelligence from their <hi>Princes Penſioners,</hi> who are obliged to acquaint them with all they can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49390:13"/>
               <p>Seventhly, Conſult likewiſe all the ſeveral <hi>Speeches, Declarations, Tryals</hi> and <hi>Tranſactions,</hi> occaſion'd by the late unhappy <hi>Wars</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> wherein you'l find more natural and uſeful Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, than is ordinarily to be met with in all the mouldy <hi>Records</hi> of antient <hi>Statiſts</hi> and <hi>Polititians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, There will be no need to adviſe you what <hi>Authors</hi> you ſhall read in <hi>Divinity;</hi> for I know ſufficient care is taken for that already; yet in my <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,</hi> next to the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> and our <hi>Churches Catechiſm,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammonds Practical Catechiſm,</hi> and thoſe Books by the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> are the beſt. And indeed all our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Writers</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for the laſt fifty or ſixty years, (who have imploy'd their Parts, Faculties and Time, in treating <hi>de omni ente,</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done the greateſt part of the World,) if accurately read and well digeſted, will furniſh you with variety of <hi>Matter,</hi> all ſorts of <hi>Methods,</hi> and a delicate <hi>Style.</hi> But then you ſhould take <hi>Advice</hi> in the choice of ſuch <hi>Books,</hi> as are <hi>approved</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49390:14"/>and moſt <hi>authentick</hi> upon every <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> that the whole Time of your <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> may be profitably imployed; for a <hi>few Books</hi> well read and throughly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, will more improve your Reaſon and Judgment, than hundreds ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally turned over, as many <hi>young Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> do.</p>
               <p>Yet there's abundance of Pleaſure in variety of Books; for when your Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties grow dull and weary of one, you may paſs to another, as your own <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> and <hi>Inclination</hi> ſhall direct; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the whole Time and Buſineſs of your <hi>Study</hi> will become a delight and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, rather than a burthen to you: Nor can any <hi>Recreation</hi> be ſo pleaſant, (this I find by experience,) nor any <hi>Labour</hi> ſo profitable to a <hi>Scholar</hi> as <hi>Study.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Laſtly, You'l find it of ſingular uſe and advantage for the improvement of your <hi>Parts,</hi> to imploy and exerciſe your <hi>Pen</hi> upon every <hi>Occaſion. Write</hi> often to your <hi>Relations</hi> and <hi>Friends;</hi> for the neglect of that is a general fault in <hi>young Students.</hi> Have always a <hi>Common-Place Book</hi> by you, (your <hi>Tutor</hi> will direct
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49390:14"/>you to the moſt uſeful <hi>Heads,</hi> and note therein the moſt remarkable, quaint, and ingenuous Paſſages you meet with in any <hi>Author,</hi> which you may afterwards have recourſe to immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon every occaſion: Obſerve like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and note in writing, all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <hi>Occurrences</hi> in your Travel; particularly the <hi>Situation</hi> of <hi>Places,</hi> the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> their <hi>Religion, Government, Policies, Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique,</hi> &amp;c. This will be of great eaſe to your <hi>Memory,</hi> and of ſingular uſe and advantage in the whole Progreſs of your Life; beſides, you'l find that your <hi>Parts, Style</hi> and <hi>Method,</hi> will be the beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by much <hi>Writing:</hi> All Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men can witneſs this from their own Experience, and is very remarkable in all our <hi>Engliſh Worthies;</hi> inſomuch that I dare be confident, if you'l apply your ſelf to this method, your Reaſon and Judgment will by degrees attain to ſuch a Habit, as will not dare to preſent you with any thing but what's very curious and excellent.</p>
               <p>Yet I would not hereby engage you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49390:15"/>to be ſo earneſt in the purſuit of your <hi>Studies,</hi> as to prejudice your own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution;</hi> for there's a Time for all things, and too much reading may prevent the Acceſs of a newer, nearer, and quicker Invention of your own: Beſides, if your Body be ſtrong, as you'l rather complain of the ſhortneſs of the Day, than be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with <hi>Study;</hi> ſo, if it be weak and feeble, the <hi>Decays</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, being alſo allowed to the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi>) either, Firſt, By a ſutable <hi>Converſation;</hi> or, Secondly, By moderate and innocent <hi>Recreations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt of theſe, namely a ſutable <hi>Converſation:</hi> When you are wearied and indiſpoſed with your <hi>Studies,</hi> a door of <hi>Conference</hi> is open, and the <hi>Converſation</hi> of learned, wiſe, and good Men, is a greater Refiner of the <hi>Spirit</hi> than <hi>Books.</hi> Yet let not this tempt you from your <hi>Studies</hi> in the Forenoon, which is the moſt proper Time to be reſerved, and at your Book; however, whilſt you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity:</hi> And herein let me adviſe you to lay down ſuch <hi>Rules</hi> to your ſelf, in obſerving thoſe ſtated
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49390:15"/>
                  <hi>Hours,</hi> as no Man ſhall be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade you to recede from them; for that when your <hi>Reſolutions</hi> are once known, as no Perſon of Ingenuity will diſturb you, ſo you'l find this <hi>Method</hi> of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this beſt part of the <hi>Day</hi> to your ſelf,) will become not only practicable, but very commendable, and of ſingular benefit to you in more inſtances than I can readily mention.</p>
               <p>But when <hi>Dinner</hi> is over, (ſo ſoon as you can with <hi>convenience</hi> and <hi>civility</hi> to the Company,) retire to your <hi>Cloſet,</hi> and pray (as in the <hi>Morning,</hi>) always concluding your <hi>Devotions</hi> in the Name of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and with the <hi>Lords Prayer:</hi> Again, <hi>read</hi> ſome por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> in the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalms</hi> for the <hi>Day,</hi> and (as before) with attentive <hi>Obſervation.</hi> (And be as careful in performing your <hi>Evening Devotions,</hi> with <hi>Thankſgivings</hi> for the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of the <hi>Day,</hi> and earneſt Prayer for your <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Protection,</hi> that night and for ever). I do not doubt but you have good
<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Common Prayer Book, Patrick</hi>'s <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Helps</hi> and particular <hi>Devotions</hi> by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49390:16"/>you for <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening,</hi> which you may uſe with your own, as God ſhall be pleas'd to enable you: But be ſure that you never lie down to reſt, till you have made your <hi>Evening Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> that whether you ſleep or wake, you may be always ſafe under the ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and protection of a gracious <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return, having performed your <hi>Devotions</hi> after <hi>Dinner,</hi> then you may either go to, or ſend for ſuch <hi>Companions</hi> as you think fit, and ſee that they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>few;</hi> for as the vitious and unlearned are not worthy of your <hi>Company</hi> and <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> ſo too many of the more learned, wiſer, and better ſort, will but increaſe the <hi>expence</hi> both of your <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Money;</hi> beſides, the <hi>Examples</hi> of others do uſually prevail more, and have a greater Influence than their <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Counſels;</hi> and by the opportunities of <hi>Converſe,</hi> either good or bad, we commonly imbibe all the Tinctures of <hi>Vice</hi> or <hi>Vertue;</hi> inſomuch that 'tis almoſt impoſſible for the moſt prudent Man to hold out long againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49390:16"/>the forcible Batteries of Cuſtom and Opportunity. But,</p>
               <p>There are no certain <hi>Rules</hi> to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for <hi>Converſe;</hi> ſeeing all Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that <hi>Kind</hi> are <hi>Occaſional,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend much upon the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Time, Place, Perſons,</hi> &amp;c. yet a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has uſually the freedom to be as inquiſitive as he pleaſes; and what would be cenſured in others as humorous <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſeneſs,</hi> or pragmatical <hi>Sawcineſs,</hi> will be interpreted in you, as an ingenuous deſire and thirſt after Knowledge: Therefore 'tis a ſingular and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Priviledge you have in this Kind above Perſons of a lower Rank, which (being improved to the beſt Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,) may very much conduce to your Intereſt and Satisfaction; for he's a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak Companion from whom you may not receive ſome benefit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <hi>wiſer.</hi> But then if you <hi>correſpond</hi> with Learned Men and Communicative, they'l freely impart to you thoſe <hi>Secrets</hi> (in a little time,) which have coſt them, and would have put you to the expence of much Pains and Travel; and if the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49390:17"/>
                  <hi>Company</hi> be below you in Parts and Learning in being free, open, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſive of what you know, and the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you repeat them they'l be more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted and confirmed to you, and impreſs them upon your Mind and Memory, in more durable and indeleble Characters.</p>
               <p>Yet give me leave to <hi>caution</hi> you in two things: And Firſt, See that you be innocently free and chearful in your <hi>Converſation:</hi> Let <hi>hoc age</hi> be your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Motto;</hi> for if a Man be ſullen, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, mopiſh, and unſeaſonably poring upon his Book or Buſineſs, he loſes the Fruits and Benefits of <hi>Converſe,</hi> nor will his <hi>Company</hi> be looked upon by others to be either <hi>profitable</hi> or <hi>diverſive.</hi> And Secondly, Avoid the other Extreme of <hi>talking too much,</hi> as troubleſome and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd; for every Man that can be a fit Companion for you, will expect to have a ſhare in the <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> It muſt needs then be a great Vanity in many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who having ſome little ſmatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Learning, (for empty Veſſels have the loudeſt Sound,) do make all Places eccho with their <hi>Latin, Italian,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49390:17"/>French,</hi> &amp;c. and Citations out of the moſt celebrated Authors; for the more that any Man ſeems to borrow from Books, he do's thereby proclaim the meanneſs of his own natural Parts, which only and properly can be call'd his own.</p>
               <p>Be reſerved in paſſing your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſpecially in what may concern the Reputations or Intereſts of other Men; your Buſineſs will be rather to enquire (as before,) and that too with all poſſible Candor and Modeſty, into the Policies and Forms of Government, all ſorts of Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore to this End endeavour to be acquainted, and <hi>converſe</hi> with Men of the greateſt Parts Sobriety and Experience; from whom you'l always receive Benefit, and note ſomething worthy your Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I would not adviſe you to avoid wholly the Converſation of your <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men,</hi> yet correſpond as little with them as poſſible; for you would find it very unprofitable upon ſeveral ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, which I leave to your own Conſideration.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49390:18"/>
               <p>Thus every thing is beautiful in its Seaſon: And we have ſeen hitherto how the chief part of your Time ſhould be imployed at your <hi>Book, Lectures,</hi> and <hi>Exerciſes</hi> in the <hi>Schools,</hi> and <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with others, whilſt you continue in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> or when ſetled in any other Place: (For upon <hi>Travel,</hi>) the Methods muſt be altered and order'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws and Dictates of Prudence and Diſcretion. And tho neither <hi>Birth,</hi> nor <hi>Quality,</hi> nor <hi>Eſtate,</hi> can give any Man a Priviledge or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be idle: Yet,</p>
               <p>Secondly, There muſt be ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Time ſet apart (which ſhould always be in the <hi>Afternoon,</hi>) for ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and innocent <hi>Refreſhments;</hi> the Diverſion and Reparation of your wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Thoughts,</hi> as well as the Eaſe and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your <hi>Body.</hi> But herein I muſt <hi>caution</hi> you, that your <hi>Recreations</hi> be <hi>moderate,</hi> endeavouring always to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine your ſelf to theſe following <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Meaſures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore your bodily <hi>Pleaſures</hi> ſhould not be <hi>expenſive</hi> of too much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49390:18"/>
                  <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>Money;</hi> both which may be very well imployed to better Purpoſes; nor <hi>cruel,</hi> nor <hi>bloody,</hi> nor <hi>ſinful;</hi> as when <hi>Paſtimes</hi> and <hi>Sports</hi> are mixed with <hi>Anger, Paſſion, Violence, Fury, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Swearing, Quarrelling, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and the like: For we ſhould uſe our <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> and <hi>Merriments,</hi> as we do <hi>Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> to our <hi>Meats,</hi> to <hi>delight</hi> and <hi>refreſh</hi> Us, that we may hereby become more active and vigorous when we return to our neceſſary <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Studies;</hi> which cannot by any means ſerve thoſe good and neceſſary <hi>Ends,</hi> unleſs they be always conducted with Reaſon and Sobriety.</p>
               <p>Hitherto of thoſe <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, Rules</hi> and <hi>Methods,</hi> which I hope may be of ſome uſe, not only to allure and invite, (tho moſt agreeable to your own temper, and therefore more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive,) but direct you too in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Management of your <hi>Studies.</hi> We paſs on now to the <hi>Second Head,</hi> which will more immediately reſpect your <hi>Manners and Deportment,</hi> as they diſpoſe to <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:49390:19"/>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49390:19"/>
               <head>ADVICE TO A YOUNG GENTLEMAN Of an Honourable FAMILY Now in His TRAVELS Beyond the SEA'S, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> PART II. <hi>Of Manners and Deportment.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE tender Care of your Worthy <hi>Parents</hi> in your vertuous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, as well as learned Education, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49390:20"/>your own <hi>natural Genius</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> might ſpare me the trouble of writing a large <hi>Eſſay</hi> of <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>Civil De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment:</hi> Yet becauſe Wickedneſs and Vice is always more inſinuative than Vertue and Goodneſs, which by ſeveral repeated Acts grows (gradually) to a cuſtom, and becomes habitual; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Perſons in your <hi>Station</hi> are uſually expoſed to more and greater <hi>Temptations</hi> than thoſe who move in a lower <hi>Orbe:</hi> Therefore without any further Apology, you'l be pleas'd to indulge me the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and freedom to become your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, or rather <hi>Monitor</hi> in a few <hi>Things.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, It will be a great Argument of Parts and Diſcretion, to be modeſt and reſerved in <hi>ſpeaking of your Self, Family,</hi> and <hi>Affairs,</hi> leſt by a ſanciful and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaning Conceit of your own <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Merits,</hi> you deſervedly incur the the Cenſure of <hi>Pragmaticalneſs</hi> and <hi>Oſtentation;</hi> from which <hi>Precipice</hi> many have dangerouſly fallen: For we know that <hi>Pride</hi> was the Sin of the <hi>fallen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> and Foundreſs of Hell, the ruine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49390:20"/>of Mankind from the beginning of the <hi>Creation,</hi> and ever ſince hateful in it ſelf, and abominable to God and all good Men: But beſides the Evil, ſuch is the Folly and Vanity of this <hi>Vice,</hi> that tho the humorous and ſelf-conceited Man has ſeldom any thing to boaſt of, yet he's uſually ſo tranſported with an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and tow'ring Ambition of what he has, as to neglect a Supply of what is wanting; and being always attended with <hi>Inſolence</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> of others, do's effectually blaſt and diſparage all other Vertues: For every Man is more inquiſitive after the <hi>Blemiſhes</hi> than <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of a proud Perſon; whereas the humble and modeſt Man may paſs ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and uncenſured, with more real Faults and Indiſcretions.</p>
               <p>Therefore have always a lowly and modeſt Opinion of your own <hi>Perſon, Quality, Acquiſitions, Merits</hi> and <hi>Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> both of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Mind;</hi> and be content that others ſhould have ſo too: For why ſhould any Man admire thoſe little Pittances of Learning, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeeing they are not properly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49390:21"/>our own, but are either begg'd or bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd from others, or have been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and acquired by dear-bought Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience? Beſides if we ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon and conſider all the Deſicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Follies and Indiſcretions of our beſt Performances, the Ignorance and Errors of our Judgments, the Perverſeneſs and Obſtinacy of our Wills, the many Sins and Infirmities we are daily guilty of, and that every thing we have may be taken away or blaſted in a moment: Such Conſiderations as theſe, would humble the <hi>proudeſt Man</hi> alive, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all the vain and inſolent Conceits of our haughty and ambitious Spirits; for ſuch proud and ſupercilious Humours are more ſutable to the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> where Men ſeem wifer than they are, than this of <hi>England,</hi> where our <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots</hi> are uſually wiſer than at firſt ſight they ſeem to be. Therefore as you are obliged to ſubdue and abandon all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring and lofty <hi>Conceits</hi> of what you are, or what you have, ſo the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to the Acceptance, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49390:21"/>you a good Eſteem and Opinion from all you converſe with.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Be <hi>prudently</hi> reſerved in cenſuring or ridiculing the Faults and Indiſcretions of other Men: For, a <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Carriage</hi> is highly eſteemed by all, but ſtrangers eſpecially. Beſides, <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> will teach and direct you how to ſubjugate all the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, Paſſions, Affections and Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations both of Soul and Body, to the Empire of Reaſon and ſound Judgment; ſo that when you have reduced all your lower Faculties to this Order and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> will direct aright, and your <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come conformable to the Laws and Rules of right Reaſon and Religion. Then, you'l manage all your Affairs <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,</hi> with the greateſt Calmneſs and Tranquillity, and be always in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of generous Ends, and the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Means and Methods of obtaining them. And thus,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, By acting according to theſe <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> you'l come by degrees to an excellent Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49390:22"/>and Habit of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> For you'l hereby prevail with your ſelf, not to indulge your <hi>Appetite,</hi> to the diſturbance and diſquiet of your rational Powers: Nor will any Man of Prudence and Sobriety endeavour to pleaſe and gratifie his <hi>Palate</hi> with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> nor his <hi>Touch</hi> with <hi>Softneſs</hi> and <hi>Effeminacy,</hi> nor his <hi>Eye</hi> with fair and gaudy <hi>Show's,</hi> nor his <hi>Smell</hi> with coſtly <hi>Perfumes:</hi> For an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate <hi>Complyance</hi> with all or any of theſe, would not only force your <hi>Reaſon</hi> to quit her Dominion and Authority, and thereby hurry you into all manner of ſin and wickedneſs, but continually diſtract your Thoughts, with a fruitleſs variety of Expectations and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The ready way then to be at peace with God, and Man, and your own Conſcience, will be to govern your ſelf according to the ſober <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Moderation,</hi> as Gods <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word</hi> and the <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>right Reaſon</hi> ſhall direct you.</p>
               <p>Now, theſe <hi>Vertues</hi> and their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite <hi>Vices</hi> having the moſt conſiderable
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49390:22"/>Aſpect upon <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> as the greateſt Examples either of Good or Evil; I ſhall therefore be more particular in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this Point of <hi>Sobriety:</hi> And for the prevention of a Shipwrack of your Intereſt and Honour, (many thouſands having ſplit their <hi>Veſſels</hi> upon this Rock,) give me leave to adviſe you in the</p>
               <p>Firſt place, To be very <hi>ſober and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate</hi> in <hi>Eating.</hi> Have recourſe always to the foregoing Rules of <hi>Prudence,</hi> and they'l teach you to conſult the Health &amp; Preſervation of the Body, that ſo it may be the fitter Manſion for your Soul: For 'tis always obſervable, that ungovern'd Luſts are the inſeparable Companions of intemperate <hi>Eating,</hi> and all other Sins are indulg'd and encourag'd by this Kind of <hi>Exceſs;</hi> whereas on the contrary, thoſe that live <hi>temperately</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Rule, are ſeldom tempted, or troubled, as the intemperate are, with ſickly and ill Humours, or deprived of the comforts and benefits of Health by raging and violent Diſtempers: For as a good Conſcience is the beſt Divinity,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49390:23"/>ſo Temperance is the beſt Phyſick, and a good Expedient thro' Gods Bleſſing, to preſerve <hi>mentem ſanam in Corpore ſano.</hi> And therefore if thro' inadvertency you ſhould tranſgreſs at any one <hi>Meal,</hi> let no Temptation allure you to a ſecond <hi>Repaſt,</hi> till by a fierce Hunger and Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you find your ſelf diſcharg'd of the former <hi>Exceſs:</hi> By which means, your Underſtanding will be always clear, and your Conſtitution firm and unſhaken; eſpecially if you take care,</p>
               <p>Secondly, To uſe the like <hi>moderation</hi> in <hi>Drinking,</hi> for your Health and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, both as to the <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Quantity</hi> of <hi>Liquors.</hi> Your <hi>Prudence</hi> will obſerve, that this is one of the reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and epidemical Sins of the Nation, and an <hi>Inlet</hi> to moſt other Sins, which many thouſands (and thoſe generally none of the meaneſt Rank,) make their chief Trade and Buſineſs; and is of late Years become ſo modiſh and faſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all Entertainments, that the many will ſcarce think themſelves welcome, unleſs the Liquor and Freedom be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them to make Beaſts of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49390:23"/>One would think that their Quality and Education ſhould reach 'em better Manners. But alas! they'l go further yet, and the moſt which is yet a higher Aggravation of their Sin and Villany,) become the Devils Factors for Damnation; and uſe the moſt baſe and ſordid Methods, not only to debauch themſelves, but knock down others. But for the prevention of all <hi>Exceſs</hi> in this Kind, be pleaſed to conſider,</p>
               <p>That <hi>intemperate Drinking</hi> is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive to, and fewel of all filthy Luſts: For Chambering and Wantonneſs is the uſual Effect of Rioting and Drukenneſs, as the moſt <hi>Debauchees</hi> find and feel by woful experience. This puts Men up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on deſperate Projects, and engages 'em in all ſorts of Wickedneſs and Villany; inſomuch, that the very moſt in their drunken Fits, will blaſpheme, ſwear, curſe, lie, backbite and rail againſt their innocent Neighbours, and do often kill and deſtroy one another: For ſome of 'em are cut off by ſudden <hi>Accidents,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in <hi>Duels,</hi> occaſion'd thro' <hi>Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and not a few of thoſe <hi>guzling He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49390:24"/>have ſumm'd up their Days at the end of a <hi>Watchmans</hi> Bill. In a word, <hi>intemperate Drinking</hi> lays a ſure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for all ſorts of lingring Diſeaſes, makes the moſt not only Beaſts, but Mad-men, and either brings them (as I have noted to you,) to a ſwift, untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and cruel <hi>Death,</hi> or a deteſtable and infamous <hi>Old Age,</hi> (which not one in a thouſand ever attains to,) and thoſe that do, are offenſive to all honeſt and vertuous Company, and to God the moſt of all: And beſides theſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Puniſhments, ſee their eternal <hi>Doom</hi> is detain'd already, if they live and die in this Sin unrepented of, and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.11, 12. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. Whereunto might be added many other parallel Paſſages to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations well weighed, might perſuade any Man to be maſter of his <hi>Appetite,</hi> and keep himſelf within the due bounds of <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration;</hi> which would not only be an extraordinary Bleſſing to private Perſons and Families, but conduce very much
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49390:24"/>to the Intereſt of the <hi>Publick:</hi> For I am confident, there's more Money ſpent in one year in exceſſive <hi>Drinking,</hi> than would very well provide for and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all the truly poor and indigent People in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore as you tender the Welfare of your Perſon and Family, and Intereſt of your Soul and Body, in this and a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Life, avoid and abandon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and Company of all diſſolute, debauched and intemperate Perſons: Let not their Allurements, nor Scoffings, nor Railings, perſuade you to a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with them in their inhumane and beaſtly <hi>Immoralities,</hi> ſo as to <hi>run with them to the ſame Exceſs of Riot,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.4. For, they are the Devils Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whom he commonly imploys, to precipitate inconſiderate Youth from the Throne of Vertue: Beſides, 'tis a moſt infectious and bewitching <hi>Vice,</hi> inſomuch, that if a Man ſhould once fall in love with, and contract a Habit of <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> 'twill be very difficult to ſhake it off; for the longer it poſſeſſeth him, the more he will delight in it; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49390:25"/>the older he grows, the more beaſtly and ſottiſh: Upon which account ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have complain'd at the laſt Hour, that this ſingle Sin has been the cauſe of all their other Wickedneſſes, which they muſt eternally ſmart for.</p>
               <p>I know the beſt of Men may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times exceed the Boundaries of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Temperance</hi> in <hi>Drinking:</hi> Now (Sir,) if ever it ſhould be your Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be overtaken with this Fault, whoſe Conſequences are ſo miſchievous, (which I beſeech you beware of;) do not remove from the place where you received it, except in ſuch a place or company where the Danger may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by your continuance therein; for hereby ſome part of the Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may be avoided, and more of the Shame and Scandal, always attending this giddy Spirit; which working in the Pate, will make one act all the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours habitual in a Mad-man. When you have obtain'd a Habit of <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> in the moderate uſe of <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> which are the proper Effects and Fruits of <hi>Prudence,</hi> theſe Vertues will diſpoſe you:</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49390:25"/>
               <p>Thirdly, For the well-governing of the other Luſts and Appetites of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> in your Abſtinence from <hi>bodily Pleaſures.</hi> Now (Sir) you are under the moſt forcible Obligations by the Laws of Nature and Chriſtianity, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void and abſtain from all <hi>carnal Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and every kind and degree of <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminacy:</hi> For unleſs you keep under your Appetite (as <hi>Prudence</hi> directs,) 'twill preſently ſet on fire the whole Courſe of Nature, and plunge both Soul and Body into moſt deſperate, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and irreparable Miſchiefs.</p>
               <p>For this kind of ſinful <hi>Exceſs</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance,</hi> ſeldom or never fails to draw Men away from God and his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; which is obſervable in that deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Inſtance of young King <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.12. who tells us from his own ſad Experience, (which might be a ſufficient Caution to all young Men,) that when they are once plung'd into thoſe <hi>Pits</hi> of <hi>Filthineſs,</hi> 'tis very difficult to retreat. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.22, 23. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.27. implying in both Paſſages, the great Perils and Dangers intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49390:26"/>rate Perſons run upon, who will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute their Wit, Learning, Honour. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and endanger their Souls, Bodies, and All, rather than not gratifie their brutiſh and unſatiable Luſts. This is not only the caſe of this great Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; for we have ſeen many ſad and miſerable Spectacles even in our own Age of the decayed Bodies, ſhatter'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and ruin'd Families, of many (otherwiſe hopeful) Young Gentlemen. And tho perhaps here and there one may eſcape the woful Effects of this Lewdneſs and Debauchery, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,) yet without repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of Life, Gods Judgments and Vengeance will certainly overtake them in another World: For <hi>Whoremongers</hi> and <hi>Adulterers</hi> God will judge; and whoſoever dies under the reigning Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Prevalence of this Sin, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>Therefore for God's ſake and your own, and as you tender the <hi>Weal</hi> of your <hi>Family,</hi> hold no <hi>Parley</hi> with your Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite in this Caſe; for if you do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in the leaſt, you are in great danger
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49390:26"/>of being over-come. Set a ſtrict <hi>Guard</hi> then upon all your <hi>Senſes,</hi> watch all the <hi>Ports</hi> and <hi>Avenues</hi> of your <hi>Soul</hi> againſt the incurſion of carnal Temptations, and have God always in your thoughts: This was young <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſecurity againſt the luſtful Temptations of his wanton and importunate <hi>Miſtriſs;</hi> ſo that by this means, if any evil Motions ſhould creep in unawares, you'l not ſuffer them to fix there; but either caſt them out, or kill them.</p>
               <p>Uſe ſtrict <hi>Temperance</hi> (as we have perſuaded before,) with Faſting and Labour; all which are powerful <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients</hi> to ſubjugate the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the beſt <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to further you in the great work and neceſſary buſineſs of <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Self-denial.</hi> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto add your moſt earneſt Prayers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for the aſſiſtance of his Grace, that you may obtain a comfortable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over your Appetites and Paſſions; which is a Duty ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that unleſs it be conſtantly and regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perform'd, all your other Natural and Moral Indeavours will prove ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49390:27"/>and to no purpoſe. And thus your Chriſtian <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> in all theſe ſeveral <hi>Inſtances,</hi> will further qualifie you,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, For the exerciſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of thoſe other excellent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> which you'l find of admirable uſe and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for the quiet and peaceable govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your whole Life; ſo that your <hi>Converſation</hi> will become not only plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, but delightful both to your ſelf and others. Now theſe <hi>Vertues</hi> do eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt, in bearing and ſuffering <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>patiently</hi> all the croſs Accidents (which you'l often meet with,) without fainting and fretting, and ſuch an even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and compoſedneſs of Mind, as is only conſonant to the Mild and Gentle, yet magnanimous Temper and Spirit of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and if all be thus well within, no Troubles nor Afflictions can vex nor diſcompoſe you from without. Beſides, when by the Aſſiſtance of God's Grace you are form'd into this admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Frame and Temper of Mind and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, you'l neither be timorous in <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49390:27"/>envious in <hi>Want,</hi> impatient under <hi>Afflictions,</hi> angry or reſtleſs at <hi>Reproaches</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> nor malicious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful under <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Affronts;</hi> but bear every croſs Event with equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity and a chearful ſubmiſſion to the Will of God, in all Straits and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whatſoever. And this is certainly the greatect Victory in the World, (and far beyond all the Conqueſts and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements we ever read of,) for a Gentleman to be maſter of his own <hi>Paſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence therefore 'twill evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, how much thoſe Perſons are to blame, who think it a piece of Honour in caſe of <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Affronts,</hi> to make the <hi>Sword</hi> Umpire of their own Life and others. And tho many great <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> have paid dear for this <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Valour,</hi> (as they are pleaſed to call it,) yet I do not find it warranted either by <hi>Prudence</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> (as a worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman obſerves;) nor will any Man that is either wiſe or pious, either give or accept a <hi>Challenge:</hi> For no <hi>Quarrel</hi> can be ſcrewed up to that pitch of Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49390:28"/>but one or both Parties muſt be arraigned as guilty of the moſt ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Folly and Madneſs in the World. Beſides, <hi>formal Duels</hi> are but a late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Devil, and never heard of in former Times, as relating to private <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Affronts;</hi> and 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that ſending of <hi>Challenges</hi> renders the Dead a greater Murderer than he that kills him, as being the immediate Author of his own Death: Nor are theſe inhumane and unchriſtian <hi>Practices</hi> ſo genteilly treated by our <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> that any Man ſhould be encouraged in this deſperate <hi>Attempt:</hi> For if the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers Legs, or his Friends procure not his Pardon or Reprieve, (tho he ſhould not die in the Encounter, yet) he runs precipitantly upon his own Death, and his Eſtate ſhall be confiſcated too, to the perpetual detriment and undoing of his <hi>Family.</hi> Beſides the <hi>Sting</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> (if he has any Conſcience at all,) and a dreadful <hi>Fear</hi> like that of <hi>Cains,</hi> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Blood, will render the whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his Life tedious and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch unfortunate Men; who will
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49390:28"/>ever after ſmell too ſtrong of <hi>Blood,</hi> to be admitted into any intimate Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Relation.</p>
               <p>Therefore in this Caſe particularly, <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> are not only a Chriſtian Vertue, but the trueſt Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſureſt Defenſative againſt all <hi>Injuries</hi> and <hi>Affronts:</hi> And as the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of theſe <hi>Vertues</hi> may probably qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the <hi>Heats</hi> and <hi>Paſſions</hi> of any quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſom and diſſolute <hi>Company</hi> you ſhall happen to engage in, (tho take all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible care to avoid ſuch <hi>Furies,</hi>) ſo this excellent Frame and Temper of Mind and Spirit, will diſpoſe you for a brighter Crown when theſe <hi>Storms</hi> are blown over. Again, The exerciſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of this <hi>Chriſtian Prudence</hi> and <hi>Moderation, Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> will further direct and enable you,</p>
               <p>Fifthly, To be moderate in uſing, and a good Husband in the management of that Patrimony and Eſtate, which <hi>Gods Providence</hi> and the <hi>Diſcretion</hi> of your <hi>Parents</hi> have allotted you. Now 'tis obſervable, that Riches and Honours do expoſe Men to the greateſt <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49390:29"/>(and tho your preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do not require much Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this Head,) yet give me leave to remark to you, That 'tis a great fault and weakneſs in many <hi>Young Gentlemen,</hi> who cannot ſee the <hi>Pomps</hi> and <hi>Vanities</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> but they muſt needs fall in love with them. Theſe ſeeming Beauties may and will tempt you (if poſſible,) to <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> and <hi>Luxury;</hi> but 'tis your own fault if you be inſnared and led captive by them: Nor ſhall you ever find any thing in thoſe vain <hi>Foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> which will be able to ſatisfie or pleaſe your rational Deſires and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations.</p>
               <p>Yet I ſhall readily grant you, that he whom God has bleſſed with a plentiful Eſtate, has many great Opportunities to do good both to himſelf and others; (for your direction herein, ſee the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman's Calling</hi>): Nor can any Man of Reaſon and Piety (tho he be rich and honourable,) come under the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of being either Idle or Extravagant: For righteous <hi>Noah</hi> did in reality ſee two Worlds (before and after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge,)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49390:29"/>and yet was not polluted with the Vices or Vanities of either; vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot</hi> was holy and chaſt in the midſt of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Houſe kept cloſe to the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo did <hi>Eliſha</hi> in the <hi>Syrian</hi> Court, and <hi>Daniel</hi> and others among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> &amp;c. Your Danger or Safety then, muſt ſlow from a Principle within you: For tho the Devil and the World may and will tempt, yet they have no power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain you: Nor can any thing ever make a Man unhappy, but a voluntary compliance with thoſe Temptations, and the baſe ſuggeſtions of his own ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Appetite. Be prudent and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate therefore in diſpoſing of your <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> (both now and always); for if you ſpend <hi>too high,</hi> you'l incur the Cenſure of <hi>Prodigality</hi> or <hi>Epicuriſm;</hi> and if <hi>too low,</hi> either of unbecoming <hi>Niggardlineſs,</hi> or fordid <hi>Covetouſneſs:</hi> Which (as an ingenious Perſon obſerves,) is like a Candle ill made, and ſmothers the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of a happy Fortune in its own Greaſe.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49390:30"/>
               <p>Sixthly, Be moderate alſo in your <hi>Habit</hi> and <hi>Apparel;</hi> let it not be youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully wanton, but grave and comely, like the Mind and Behaviour of the Wearer. But do not by any means ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the Humour of Bravery: For our <hi>Clothes</hi> ſhould rather humble, than puff us up, being always the viſible <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns</hi> of our Sin and Slavery; nor ſhall any Man be eſteemed for this <hi>ſort of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance,</hi> but by Fools and Wantons.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, I ſhall but add one <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi> more, and that will be of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral uſe and neceſſary importance, in the prudent, moderate, patient, peaceable and chriſtian Conduct of your whole life; which will render your Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion pleaſant and profitable to your ſelf, and acceptable to all vertuous and good Men. And this will be the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and conſcientious Management of all your <hi>Thoughts, Words</hi> and <hi>Actions.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, For the government of your <hi>Thoughts.</hi> Now (Sir,) if you be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and reſerved, ſo as not (willingly) to conceive or foſter an evil <hi>Thought,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49390:30"/>you'l then be afraid to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> or <hi>act</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing contrary to your own Reaſon and Conſcience. And to this End <hi>think</hi> often (as before) of the <hi>quatuor Noviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima,</hi> Death and Judgment, Heaven and Hell; which thro the aſſiſtance of God's Grace, may keep all the ſinful Excurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your Thoughts under ſo much reſtraint, as you'l not readily and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly conceive any thing that ſhall be either ſinful or irregular. And this will be an excellent Diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the Government of the <hi>Tongue,</hi> which ſhould be always kept under a ſtrict guard: For <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, That Life and Death are in the power of it. And <hi>Euripides</hi> truly affirms, That every licentious and unbridled <hi>Tongue</hi> ſhall in the end find it ſelf unfortunate: For we ſee by daily experience, that all <hi>Quarrels, Miſchief, Hatred,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> ariſeth from unadviſed <hi>Speech;</hi> and in much <hi>Talking</hi> there are many Errours, from which your Enemies will take the moſt dangerous Advantage. Beſides, all ſcurrilous, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, profane, idle, uncharitable, filthy,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49390:31"/>and wanton <hi>Communication,</hi> is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinful and impertinent, but altogether unbecoming a Gentleman; whoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is uſually a Pattern to others, and for whoſe ſins they muſt be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (if they be Patterns of wickedneſs) as well as their own.</p>
               <p>Set a watch then always before the doors of your Lips, that no vain <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> proceed out of your Mouth; and pray earneſtly unto God, that he would ſo ſanctifie your Speech, that Truth, Integrity and Innocence, may be the Rule and Standard of all your <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> And as it will be very happy for you if you obſerve theſe Rules, ſo 'twill be as neceſſary to avoid the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> of thoſe whoſe <hi>Tongues</hi> are profane and licentious. Do not by any means liſten to, nor give the leaſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to <hi>Whiſperers, Tale-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>inquiſitive Perſons,</hi> who buſie themſelves with the Affairs of other Men, that creep into Houſes as <hi>Spies,</hi> to hear and learn <hi>News,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them not: For I have always obſerved them to be baſe and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49390:31"/>few of them thrive and proſper, nor ſhall they ever be reſpected amongſt worthy and wiſe Men. But,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Be circumſpect and prudent in the Management of all your <hi>Actions.</hi> Set your ſelf againſt all Sins in general, and every one in particular, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, againſt thoſe whereunto your Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Diſpoſition are the moſt incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; for theſe will require the greateſt Diligence and Endeavour to overcome and ſubdue them. Do not indulge your ſelf in any one Luſt, neither commit the leaſt ſin with delight and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; becauſe, even thoſe which we think are the ſmalleſt, will prove De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy's and Incentives to greater; vain and ſinful <hi>Thoughts</hi> proceeding to <hi>Words,</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> to <hi>Deeds:</hi> So that in this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> a Man knows not where to ſtop, till he has plunged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the moſt dangerous and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Miſchiefs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then on the other hand, for your <hi>Poſitive Duties;</hi> you ſhould always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe God's Glory, the happineſs of your ſelf and others, as the <hi>End,</hi> and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49390:32"/>Word and the Dictates of ſober Reaſon, as the Rule and Standard to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern all your Affairs by: For without this, your beſt <hi>Endeavours</hi> will prove either unprofitable or ſinful. Whereas, if you obſerve this <hi>Method,</hi> and your <hi>Intentions</hi> be <hi>ſincere,</hi> tho you fail in many Inſtances of Duty, and unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall into ſome <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> yet God will be gracious in not imputing them, and paſs Judgment upon you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the general Frame and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of your Life, if you do not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wickedly <hi>continue</hi> in any <hi>known Sin,</hi> or the <hi>neglect</hi> of any <hi>known Duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis obſervable hence, what Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions you lie under, to avoid the moſt accurſed and tempting Company of profane <hi>Swearers,</hi> gluttonous <hi>Perſons, Wine-Bibbers,</hi> unchaſt <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> &amp;c. I have ſingled out thoſe <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> (on purpoſe) which are moſt inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to <hi>Youth,</hi> and given you the moſt ſeaſonable <hi>Advice</hi> I can think of, to vanquiſh and overcome them. Reject therefore every Temptation to ſin and wickedneſs in the firſt Aſſault, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49390:32"/>Conqueſt will be eaſie and certain. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and deplore your paſt Failings, and humbly beg the aſſiſtance of God's Grace and Spirit, that you may be more watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful over your ſelf and ways for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Now the beſt and moſt certain Means to avoid <hi>greater Sins,</hi> is to make Conſcience of the <hi>leſs:</hi> (For the <hi>leaſt Sin</hi> is damnable in the ſight of God); and when the work of Regeneration is wrought in you, beware of Relapſing; conſider the dangers of habitual Sin and Apoſtaſie from Grace, and exert all your Endeavours to live in the exerciſe of a Conſcience void of offence both towards God and Man: For ſo the whole Time of your ſhort aboad in this World, will be pleaſant and comfortable, and your Death happy.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other little things I deſire to note to you before I leave this <hi>Point.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Beware of <hi>Swimming,</hi> which you'l probably be allured to in thoſe <hi>Low Countries,</hi> the moſt being dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in that Art: For tho it may ſave a Mans Life in caſe of neceſſity, yet a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49390:33"/>vain Curroſity herein may expoſe you to the greateſt Dangers and Hazards. Therefore if you ſhould attempt it for your Pleaſure, exceed not your own Depth; and in ſeeking to ſave another, have a care you drown not your <hi>ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Your <hi>Geſture and Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhould neither be light, nor inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, nor wanton: For the Life and Soul of true Honour, is in generous Qualities, and a modeſt and affable <hi>Carriage;</hi> but yet with a comely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to your ſelf, and ſuch as becomes a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> whoſe Mind is furniſhed with worthy and generous Spirits. But in this <hi>Point</hi> (as in his abſtinence from the <hi>Vices,</hi> and practice of all the <hi>Vertues</hi> hitherto recommended,) you have an admirable Pattern in your dear and worthy <hi>Father,</hi> almoſt beyond Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; whoſe temper and ſweetneſs of Diſpoſition has deſervedly recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to the Favour, and made him honourable and reſpected amongſt all Perſons of all Ranks and Conditions. Yet be careful to avoid the other <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme</hi> of affected <hi>Eaſineſs</hi> or <hi>Compliance,</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49390:33"/>leſt your good Diſpoſition ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by others <hi>Deceit,</hi> and your own too much <hi>Credulity:</hi> For too much <hi>Familiarity</hi> and <hi>Fawning</hi> is always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded either with <hi>Flattery</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, What concerns your <hi>Bodily Deportment, Wreſtling, Fencing,</hi> and other Feats of <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Military Skill;</hi> and how far all or any of theſe are expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient or neceſſary to be underſtood or practiſed, I muſt leave to your ſelf, and better Judgments, for Advice and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; for theſe are not my <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What other <hi>Vertues</hi> or <hi>Vices</hi> may occur in your Converſation with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (which my deſigned Brevity and the Occaſion I write upon, have perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me to omit,) you ſhould note and obſerve them, and make that uſe of them, at leaſt to improve and correct your own: For what you diſlike or admire in others, ſtudy and endeavour to avoid the Evil, and ſtrive to imitate what is vertuous and commendable. And when you have ſeriouſly conſider'd
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49390:34"/>all thoſe ſeveral <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Arguments,</hi> which under this <hi>Head</hi> do concern your <hi>Manners</hi> and <hi>Deportment;</hi> you'l be pleas'd to go one ſtep farther to the laſt Branch of this faithful and friendly <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> which will have a more peculiar Reſpect to your <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the Second Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49390:34"/>
               <head>ADVICE TO A YOUNG GENTLEMAN Of an Honourable FAMILY Now in His TRAVELS Beyond the SEA'S, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> PART III. <hi>Of RELIGION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Buſineſs of <hi>Religion</hi> is the grand Concernment that all of us are ſent into the World to mind;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49390:35"/>and our eternal <hi>Happineſs</hi> or <hi>Miſery</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the right <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>miſtakes</hi> about it. We had need therefore be very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate in the choice of that <hi>Religion</hi> we intend to live and die in, and venture our eternal Salvation upon.</p>
               <p>Now, there are many <hi>Opinions</hi> in the World concerning <hi>Religion;</hi> and we may be eaſily impoſed on and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if we make not a prudent and wiſe <hi>Choice.</hi> I ſhall not trouble you with an account of <hi>Heatheniſm, Mahometa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> and <hi>Judaiſm:</hi> For theſe are all <hi>falſe Religions,</hi> and contrary to the whole <hi>ſcope</hi> and <hi>deſign</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> which being without the Lines of Chriſtian Communication, we leave 'em to themſelves and the righteous Judgment of God. We <hi>Chriſtians</hi> know no other way to Salvation but <hi>One,</hi> and that's by <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we think our ſelves obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> with all our Hearts, and <hi>live</hi> according to them: For there's no other name un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven whereby we can expect or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49390:35"/>hope for Salvation, but the Name of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Acts 4.12.</p>
               <p>Yet there are many <hi>Differences,</hi> not only <hi>Circumſtantial</hi> but <hi>Fundamental,</hi> even amongſt thoſe that are called <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> which diſturb the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ruine the <hi>Souls</hi> of many private <hi>Perſons,</hi> as will appear more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afterwards. But 'tis more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately my Deſign to recommend to you, and inforce the <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the truly Primitive and Reformed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as now ſolemnly and publickly profeſs'd, and by <hi>Law</hi> eſtabliſh'd in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have not the leaſt cauſe to doubt or ſuſpect, but that your <hi>Parents</hi> did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly weigh and conſider (when they ſent you abroad,) the <hi>Minority</hi> of your <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> which (yet) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your own extraordinary care and caution, may hurry you unawares into the peril of <hi>Miſcarriage.</hi> For alas! how many young <hi>Gentlemen</hi> have loſt their Hopes and themſelves in <hi>Foreign Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures,</hi> and return'd home as empty of Grace and other vertuous Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49390:36"/>as full of Words, Vanity, and other vitious Habits and Inclinations? Now (Sir,) if you ſhould unhappily <hi>Miſcarry,</hi> which the Lord of his great Mercy prevent; as it would be the greateſt <hi>miſchief</hi> to your <hi>ſelf;</hi> ſo not only your <hi>Parents</hi> hopes of your <hi>Youth,</hi> but the Staff and Comfort of their <hi>Age</hi> will lie a bleeding, to their unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>Sorrow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Conſiderations</hi> have very much affected me, which I took the freedom to mention to ſome of your Friends, when I firſt heard of their Deſign of ſending you beyond <hi>Sea;</hi> and upon more due and ſerious deliberation, do now with more conſidence (yet hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) communicate my Thoughts to you upon theſe <hi>Subjects:</hi> For I am very well aſſured, (that conſidering me as a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> and <hi>True Friend,</hi>) I ſhall not incur the leaſt <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> of being (herein) too bold or preſumptuous; and will think my ſelf ſufficiently apaid, if thro God's Bleſſing, I may be an happy Inſtrument in doing the leaſt good to your <hi>Soul.</hi> I know it would be the greateſt Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49390:36"/>to your <hi>ſelf,</hi> as well as a Comfort to all your <hi>Friends,</hi> if you be perſuaded by any <hi>means</hi> to fall in love with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> betimes, and <hi>remember your Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator in the Days of your Youth,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1. This has been for many Ages the glory and ſupport of your Family, which has been always eminent for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Loyalty; nor could there ever be leſs Danger of a degenerous Heir, (not to ſlatter you Sir, nor puff you up,) nor greater Hopes of its eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment to future Generations.</p>
               <p>But before we come to the Point, give me leave to note to you (for your greater Security,) That you'l be in danger of meeting with many <hi>Brokers</hi> of <hi>Villany,</hi> whoſe Trade and Buſineſs it is to pervert, and do live upon the Spoils and Ruins of <hi>Young Gentlemen;</hi> inſomuch that ſcarce any Perſon of your Quality can travel into <hi>Foreign Parts,</hi> but he ſhall be mightily careſs'd, and treated with ſo much reſpect and civility, as if it were a pleaſure to be <hi>ſeduced.</hi> We know very well what <hi>Stratagems</hi> are uſed by ſome Men, to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49390:37"/>undermine the ſacred <hi>Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> inſomuch that (before his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Declaration of Indulgence</hi>) neither <hi>Laws</hi> nor <hi>Penalties</hi> could reſtrain them. What then will they not dare to attempt within their own Territories and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, eſpecially when they meet with Perſons of Temper and Quality, who are inclin'd and diſpos'd (as you are) to <hi>Religion?</hi> And ſeeing alſo they have not only free ſcope and priviledge, but encouragement to ſeduce; ſo, that 'tis next to impoſſible not to be aſſaulted (at leaſt) by their cloſe and cunning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations.</p>
               <p>There have been, alaſs! too many perverted already; the loſs of whom joyned with the Churches, we have ſufficient cauſe to lament: And indeed 'tis a great wonder we have loſt no more, (and let us praiſe God for it,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the importunate <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Plauſibleneſs</hi> of our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> on the right hand and on the left; who like thoſe infected with the <hi>Plague,</hi> have always an itching deſire of tainting
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49390:37"/>others. Wherefore none can blame the Clergy of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> if we be as zealous for Truth, as our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Falſhood; which Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone might be a ſufficient <hi>Apology</hi> for this Undertaking.</p>
               <p>I have read (Sir) of ſome <hi>Countries</hi> (I wiſh your Curioſity may not carry you thither) whoſe chief Vertues (mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly ſpeaking,) do very much border either on Impiety or Superſtition; and yet thoſe very Places (as <hi>Travellers</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,) which are moſt worth ſeeing, are of all others the moſt contagious. Now 'tis no ſmall difficulty for a Young Gentleman to be chaſt and vertuous in the midſt of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and few have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd thither, however they may pleaſe themſelves with variety of <hi>Objects,</hi> and returned home without ſome dangerous Tincture, either of Sin and Wickedneſs, or Schiſm and Sedition.</p>
               <p>Thus I have noted in general, what <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Hazards</hi> you are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to amongſt <hi>Foreigners;</hi> and the greateſt of all is, the danger of being corrupted and contaminated in your
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49390:38"/>
                  <hi>Religion and Manners:</hi> And 'tis certain, tho your <hi>Tutors</hi> be never ſo careful, yet much muſt be left to your own Temper and Inclination, how to ſever Good from Evil: For there's no Man proves Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Superſtitious, or extreamly Wicked on a ſudden, but thro ſeveral Declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, falls by degrees from Vertue and Religion. Seeing then ſo many Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and Snares may await you in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Place where you come, (which no Mans Prudence can foreſee,) and your own Heart prove deceitful and forward to betray you: Therefore I beſeech you, be conſtantly upon your Guard; and if your <hi>Tutors</hi> ſhould either be negligent or perſidious, (as many have been in the like Truſt, and I could name ſome of them,) yet thro the Aſſiſtance of God's Grace, you may ſecure your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> inviolable.</p>
               <p>But for the further prevention of their <hi>Machinations,</hi> who lie in wait to deceive, and your Eſtabliſhment and Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Religion of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I offer theſe Three following <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> to your ſerious and impartial <hi>Conſideration.</hi> And,</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49390:38"/>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall give you a true (tho ſhort) Account of the Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both as to her Doctrin and Worſhip, or Diſcipline; which I hope may for ever oblige you to continue in her <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, We ſhall enquire a little into the Principles and Practices of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> wherein they chiefly differ from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s:</hi> A Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all others (within the Pail of the Chriſtian Church,) the moſt pleaſing and delightful to Fleſh and Blood: A Religion which no Man ſcarce can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with; eſpecially if he has been bred up in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but muſt offer violence to his own Reaſon and Conſcience, if he pretends to either.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We ſhall conſider the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions, Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Arguments,</hi> which our Brethren of the <hi>Non-conformity</hi> have urged in their own Defence, to palliate their <hi>Separation</hi> from our <hi>Communion,</hi> and ſeduce others: By all which, I hope 'twill evidently appear, that there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the leaſt colour of Reaſon, nor any thing like Argument to tempt, much
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49390:39"/>leſs to perſuade you, or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Parts and Education, (who is not blinded with Paſſion, Intereſt or Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,) to ſeparate from the moſt truly Orthodox, and beſt conſtituted Church in the whole World; I mean the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Of all theſe ſeverally. And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Of the <hi>Religion</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> both as to its <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> And Firſt, Concerning her <hi>Doctrin:</hi> Wherein 'tis moſt plain and evident, That we have a clear Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all <hi>Fundamental Truths</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> in our <hi>Creeds, Commandments, Lords Prayer,</hi> and the Doctrin of the <hi>Two Sacraments;</hi> which every Orthodox and Believing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in the whole World, will readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Sabbaths</hi> are duly obſerved and kept, with the greateſt Reverence and Solemnity. God's <hi>Holy Word</hi> is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully preach'd; his <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> duly adminiſtred, according to our Bleſſed Saviours own Inſtitution. We worſhip <hi>God,</hi> viz. the <hi>One Divine Eſſence,</hi> and <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Perſons,</hi> in Spirit
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49390:39"/>and Truth; in and thro' Chriſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Mediation of Saints and Angels. We hope for, and believe the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of <hi>Sins,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of our <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Bodies,</hi> by the Merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone, thro' the Mercies of <hi>God,</hi> and upon the condition of a ſincere and unſeigned <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance:</hi> Which <hi>Repentance</hi> in the Judgment of our <hi>Church,</hi> implies a true <hi>Sight</hi> and <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of, hearty <hi>arrow</hi> for, and the <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>forſaking</hi> of all our former <hi>Sins;</hi> with a ſtedfaſt <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> never to return to them again, with any <hi>conſent, delight</hi> or <hi>approbation,</hi> and the uſe of all poſſible <hi>Endeavours</hi> to put theſe <hi>Reſolutions</hi> in practice, even to our Lives End: So, that if we ſhall at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time fall into the commiſſion of the leaſt <hi>Sin,</hi> or the neglect of any <hi>Duty,</hi> either wilfully, or by infirmity and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize; we do again ſeriouſly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly renew our <hi>Repentance,</hi> and are never at peace with our Selves and in our Conſciences, till we be again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God, or our Neighbour, whom we have offended. And this we do as well after as before our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49390:40"/>not daring to continue in any <hi>one ſin unrepented of, unreformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we have thus renounced and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd <hi>Sin,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> as our deadly <hi>Enemies,</hi> we think our ſelves further oblig'd to magnifie and adorn our <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> by the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Fruits</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and true <hi>Holineſs, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity, Purity</hi> and <hi>Sobriety,</hi> Tit. 2.12. and to perform all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe <hi>Duties</hi> both to God and Man, without <hi>Partiality,</hi> without <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi> This is a ſhort <hi>Specimen</hi> of the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> which in all and every <hi>particular</hi> are warranted and recommended to Us by God's infallible <hi>Word,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current Suffrages and Confeſſions of all the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Pureſt Ages</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And as the <hi>Doctrin</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> is Sound and Orthodox, ſo,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Our <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> is truly <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical:</hi> For there's not one ſingle Paſſage in our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> and <hi>Church Service,</hi> and <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> (our moſt rigid <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49390:40"/>being Judges,) that is either <hi>Anti-Scriptural</hi> or <hi>Sinful,</hi> but do all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much conduce to <hi>Decency, Order, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> and the <hi>Edification</hi> of its <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</hi> All which, I could eaſily make appear to you by an Induction of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; inſomuch that there's not one <hi>National Church</hi> under the Cope of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that's more Orthodox than Ours, in Her whole <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Politie.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and examine our <hi>Liturgy, Articles, Homilies, Canons</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> &amp;c. and there you'l find a truly <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical Spirit</hi> in the diſpoſition of the ſeveral <hi>Parts,</hi> for the Honour and Glory of <hi>God,</hi> and Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for a further Teſtimony hereof, and your own particular Satisfaction, read (when you can have the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thoſe Books, and leiſure to read 'em,) <hi>Hookers Eccleſiaſtical Politie,</hi> Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s large Volume on our <hi>Church Liturgy,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Falkner</hi>'s <hi>Libertas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica;</hi> which <hi>Triumvirate</hi> are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently able to anſwer all the <hi>Doubts</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:49390:41"/>and <hi>Scruples</hi> of any unbiaſt and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced <hi>Reader.</hi> Beſides, I can give you a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of ſuch <hi>Books,</hi> when you pleaſe to command it, as have treated ſo learnedly, judiciouſly and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cingly of the <hi>Religion of the Church of England,</hi> in all the Points of <hi>Faith, Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as will furniſh you with ſuch Reaſons and Arguments, as neither <hi>Papiſt</hi> nor <hi>Phanatick</hi> were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet able to anſwer.</p>
               <p>Let your <hi>Religion</hi> then, and that <hi>Church</hi> into which you were admitted and initiated by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and in whoſe <hi>Communion</hi> you have been hitherto edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, be as dear to you as your <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> Remit nothing of your Love and Affection, Zeal and Courage, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, when you are thereunto law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called: For the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> has been tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Us by our pious <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> with all the <hi>Sanctions</hi> both of <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority;</hi> and as ſure as there is a God, the <hi>Religion</hi> which you profeſs came down from <hi>Heaven:</hi> For the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> has conſign'd and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49390:41"/>confirm'd it to Us, by the Effuſion of his own precious <hi>Blood,</hi> and the Suffrage of many <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> in this Kingdom; ſo that you have not the leaſt reaſon to ſcruple your <hi>Compliance</hi> with, and <hi>Conformity</hi> to it.</p>
               <p>If therefore an <hi>Angel,</hi> or <hi>Devil,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ill <hi>Men,</hi> ſhould at any time ſuggeſt the contrary to you, have no <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> with him, but reject him as an utter Enemy and Impoſtor. And when you have more leiſure, opportunity and experience, your <hi>Curioſity</hi> may lead you to read over and conſider the <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin Churches;</hi> wherein you'l find the true <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Things</hi> and <hi>Times,</hi> the <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Proceedings, Increaſes, Encounters, Yieldings,</hi> and <hi>Reſtaurations</hi> of the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;</hi> and what the <hi>Primitive Fathers</hi> did and ſuffer'd for the propagation of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> and the intereſt of the <hi>Church:</hi> And herein you'l alſo ſee the <hi>Conformity</hi> of our <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Men,</hi> ſince the beginning of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> to the <hi>Primitive Pattern.</hi> And when you have thus made ſome
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49390:42"/>conſiderable <hi>Progreſs</hi> in inquiring into the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> and <hi>Superſtructures</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> you'l be better able to judge of the <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> of thoſe that differ from Us. But till you have more time and convenience to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your <hi>ſelf</hi> as to the Particulars, I ſhall preſent you,</p>
               <p>Secondly, With a true and brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Popery,</hi> or the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to thoſe <hi>Particulars</hi> wherein they differ from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> For which cauſe, we are forced to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from them, ſince we cannot communicate with them without ſin; nor have we departed further from 'em, than they have departed from Themſelves, and the Truth.</p>
               <p>Now for Method's ſake, we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo, Firſt, The <hi>Principles</hi> or <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin;</hi> And, Secondly, The <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>pretended Catholicks</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church:</hi> Whereby 'twill evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that <hi>Popery</hi> (if rightly underſtood,) is no ſuch beautiful and charming Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as to allure any Man of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49390:42"/>
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> to fall in love with it. And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, For the <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> and we are obliged to call them ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſo eſteem'd and account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their own <hi>Church:</hi> For ſince their <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> no Man can properly be admitted into the <hi>Romiſh Communion</hi> (however in <hi>Popiſh Countries</hi>) but ſhall be cenſured and condemned as a damn'd <hi>Heretick,</hi> unleſs he believes as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">That a Mortal Man, as the <hi>Pope</hi> in <hi>Cathedra,</hi> (or as ſome ſay, with his <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Cardinals</hi>) is infallible, knows all things, and can err in nothing; that he directs, informs, animates, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands both in <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Purgatory;</hi> expounds <hi>Scripture,</hi> forgives <hi>Sins,</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizeth <hi>Saints,</hi> creates new <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> and in all theſe, (and many other of the ſame Stamp and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter) is as abſolute and infallible as his <hi>Maker.</hi>
                  </q> [But they are not yet agreed amongſt themſelves where to fix this Infallible Judgment, whether in the <hi>Pope</hi> alone, or <hi>Council,</hi> or the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Council;</hi> and therefore their <hi>Church</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49390:43"/>and <hi>Pope,</hi> for any thing they have yet prov'd or determin'd, are erroneous and fallible in the firſt Principle of their <hi>New Creed,</hi> and monſtrous Doctrin of <hi>Infallibility.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">The the <hi>Pope</hi> is the <hi>Supreme Head,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s chief <hi>Vicar</hi> in, and has an Unlimited <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over the whole <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> that he has power to diſpenſe with the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and can ſet up <hi>Laws</hi> of his own deviſing, which obliges all Men's Conſciences to pay him the Tribute of Fealty &amp; Obedience, as will more fully appear afterwards.</q> [This is a grand Uſurpation upon the Rights and Priviledges of Kings, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and all other Chriſtian Biſhops; two parts of Chriſtendom having reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Authority, and that upon moſt reaſonable and juſt grounds: For the <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> was limited for the five firſt <hi>Centuries</hi> to the <hi>Suburbiarion Regions,</hi> and had only a <hi>Primacy</hi> of <hi>Order,</hi> not <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over his <hi>Fellow Biſhops.</hi> See <hi>Hammond</hi>'s <hi>Fundament.</hi> Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> upon the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fulwood</hi>'s <hi>Roma ruit.</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:49390:43"/>Which Uſurpation do's alſo directly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Kingly Office.]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council of Trent. Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Canon</hi> 1.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">That the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> is tranſubſtantiated into the real <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which was ſacrificed for our Sins upon the Croſs at <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> the Colour and other accidental Qualities of the Elements only remaining with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Subſtance.</q> [This violates the Truth of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Human Nature, which themſelves do confeſs, is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and yet according to their <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> muſt be in a thouſand places on Earth at the ſame time; contradicts the holy Scripture, Man's beſt Reaſon, common Senſe, and the Nature and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> holy <hi>Supper.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 465. <hi>Hiſt. Council Trent.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <q rend="inline">That there is no real difference between <hi>Chriſt</hi> on the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Maſs;</hi> it is the very ſame in both, only differing in the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of <hi>Offering:</hi> For on the <hi>Croſs</hi> he offer'd himſelf immediatly, in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49390:44"/>the <hi>Maſs</hi> he offers himſelf by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of his <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-Prieſts.</hi>
                  </q> [Which <hi>Doctrin</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Maſs,</hi> is one of the greateſt <hi>Idols</hi> that ever was invented in the World: For a piece of <hi>Bread</hi> is made the <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the pardoning all <hi>Sin;</hi> is worſhiped as <hi>God,</hi> and of ſingular benefit not only for the <hi>Living</hi> but the <hi>Dead:</hi> And this they are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, tho the Apoſtle has told them in expreſs terms, That there remains no more Sacrifice for Sins, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> once <hi>appear'd to put away ſin by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of himſelf,</hi> Heb. 9.26.]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council of Trent, Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>Canon</hi> 3.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">That <hi>Good Works</hi> are meritorious of <hi>Grace</hi> and eternal <hi>Life;</hi> which are not ſo much given of God freely and out of liberality, as out of debt.</q> [Which Doctrin deſtroys <hi>Juſtification</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Merits</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> who came down from Heaven on purpoſe to redeem us from all Iniquity, and tells us, when we have done the beſt we can, we are unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servants, deſerving nothing but
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49390:44"/>Hell and Damnation every hour.]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Decret. Council Flor. about</hi> 200 <hi>Years ago.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <q rend="inline">That there's a certain place call'd <hi>Purgatory,</hi> wherein, as in a Priſon, Souls are purged after this Life, that were not fully purged here; to the intent they may enter pure into Heaven.</q> [Which <hi>Article</hi> of their <hi>New Creed,</hi> deſtroys the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his meritorious <hi>Interceſſion</hi> with the <hi>Father</hi> for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> makes good Men afraid to die, being a terrible thing (as their <hi>Prieſts</hi> repreſent it,) to enter into <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and bad Men leſs care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to prepare for Death, becauſe a great part of their buſineſs may be done by other hands when they are gone.]</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council of Trent. Seſſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Canon</hi> 9.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">That, if any ſay, that the <hi>Clergy</hi> who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> or <hi>Regulars</hi> who have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemnly profeſſed <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> may contract <hi>Marriage;</hi> and that ſuch <hi>Contract</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Law,</hi> and their own <hi>Vow,</hi>) is valid; and that the contrary Aſſertion is no other than to condemn Marriage; and that all (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49390:45"/>they have vowed <hi>Chaſtity,</hi>) may contract Marriage, that do find they have not the Gift of Continency; let him be accurſed: Foraſmuch as God will not deny this Gift to thoſe who rightly ſeek it, neither will he ſuffer Us to be tempted above what we are able.</q> [Now this Doctrin is expreſly contrary to the Word of God, which ſaith, That <hi>Marriage is honourable in all,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4. See alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 2, 4, 5, 11, 12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1, 2, 8, 9. Beſides, the Prohibition of <hi>Prieſts Marriage,</hi> has been the cauſe of much Lewdneſs and Villany, as Adultery, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, Inceſt, Sodomy, Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council of Trent. Seſſ.</hi> 9.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">That the <hi>Saints</hi> reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up their <hi>Prayers</hi> for <hi>Men,</hi> it is good and profitable hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to <hi>invocate</hi> them; and that we may obtain Benefits of <hi>God,</hi> thro his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord, who is our only Redeemer and Saviour to have recourſe to their Prayers, Aid and Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> [This Doctrin has no Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in, nor Warrant from God's
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49390:45"/>Word: For there's not one Precept nor Example of praying to <hi>Saints</hi> in the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> nor Promiſe that ſuch <hi>Prayers</hi> ſhall be heard and accepted; but the contrary is every where evident. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this <hi>Practice</hi> is irrational and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd: For the Saints (and Angels) are neither <hi>omnipreſent</hi> nor <hi>omnipercipient;</hi> and therefore they cannot hear Us.
<note place="margin">Caſſand. de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. &amp; Interceſſ. Sanct.</note>And they do alſo ſolemnly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> many of their <hi>reputed Saints,</hi> whoſe Saintſhip, nay, whoſe Exiſtence (ſays one of their own celebrated Authors,) is very queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.]</p>
               <p>Not to trouble you with Citations at large, there are ſeveral other known and received Doctrins of their Church, which bear the ſame <hi>Impreſſion</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter;</hi> but thoſe I have mention'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready being the moſt conſiderable, the reſt will either ſtand or fall by 'em. Yet their Doctrin of <hi>Oral Tradition</hi> (which I had almoſt omitted,) deſerves its place amongſt the reſt: For this vilifies the Holy Scripture, deſtroys its Authority
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49390:46"/>and Sufficiency, by a certain Dependance upon the Church; whereby they make our Saviour's <hi>Prophetical Office</hi> a meer <hi>Nullity,</hi> in ſaying no leſs, than that He has not ſufficiently reveal'd the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> but all the World muſt be beholden to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> for their <hi>Oral Tradition.</hi> In a word, all their Pardons, Confeſſions, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Satisfactions, Merits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contradict the great End and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of our Saviours <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and ſet up the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> in his ſtead.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>New Articles</hi> of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which (as incredible and abſurd as they are) the Subjects of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion are bound to believe, under the pain and peril of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Anathema.</hi> And indeed, they are all <hi>New,</hi> (you may ſee the Original of 'em in Dr. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>'s <hi>Advice</hi> to the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi>) and wholly unknown to the Old Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in her Primitive and Goſpel Purity: For theſe Errors and Deluſions ſeem to have been contrived on purpoſe, for the Support and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Pride and Covetouſneſs
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49390:46"/>of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and his <hi>Clergy,</hi> as well as the Advancement of the <hi>State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and <hi>Grandeur</hi> of their <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could eaſily make it appear to you in all the <hi>Particulars,</hi> that there's not one of theſe <hi>Articles</hi> that has any Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Scripture or Primitive Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but are contrary to both, and do undermine and overthrow almoſt all the <hi>Articles</hi> of our Chriſtian Faith. But what I have ſaid already concerning theſe <hi>Doctrins,</hi> may be a ſufficient <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to you not to venture your eternal Salvation upon ſuch a Bottom, leſt you communicate with them in their Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. I have taken ſome pains to digeſt the whole <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Controverſie</hi> into Order and Method, for the ſatisfaction of my Self and Friends, (which I thought of neceſſary uſe at this time.) There are other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Authors which may be more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, but you may command this if you pleaſe; 'tis not very large, yet <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical.</hi> But to return: As the <hi>Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> (in thoſe Inſtances wherein they differ
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49390:47"/>from Us) are heterodox, abſurd and erroneous; ſo,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Their <hi>Practices</hi> are the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and genuin Reſults and Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch <hi>Principles.</hi> Not to mention their private and perſonal <hi>Immoralities,</hi> which may conſiſt well enough with that <hi>Religion,</hi> eſpecially conſidering the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> allowed them, (which do more profeſſedly belong to thoſe of that Communion than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) we ſhall conſider their <hi>Practices</hi> as <hi>Popiſh,</hi> which are warranted to them by the <hi>Examples</hi> and <hi>Sanctions</hi> of their <hi>Superiours.</hi> And of this Rank are,</p>
               <p>Their Worſhiping of <hi>Images, Relicks, Croſſes, Angels, Saints,</hi> and particularly the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> all which are a moſt direct Violation of the <hi>Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment;</hi> and therefore they leave it out of all their <hi>Catechiſms, Manuals, Maſs-Books,</hi> &amp;c. leſt it ſhould riſe up in Judgment againſt them; which <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices</hi> are alſo contrary to the whole <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrin</hi> both of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:49390:47"/>
               <p>Such alſo are their Dealings with the <hi>Laity,</hi> who rob them of the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> in denying them the reading of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>Cup</hi> in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> and in commanding the whole <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to be celebrated and perform'd in an unknown <hi>Tongue;</hi> which few of their <hi>Laity,</hi> and perhaps ſome of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> do not underſtand. Tho they cannot but know that our bleſſed Saviour has expreſly commanded, that <hi>all</hi> (indefinitely) both <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> ſhould <hi>ſearch the Scriptures, drink of that holy Cup,</hi> and <hi>pray with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and <hi>pray with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:</hi> Which no Perſon can in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, unleſs he underſtands <hi>Latin</hi> well, and the ſtrange <hi>Mumblings</hi> of their <hi>Prieſts;</hi> who being generally too igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant themſelves, are afraid that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould know it. <hi>O horrendum Nefas!</hi> that ſuch <hi>Practices</hi> as theſe ſhould be ſo much as tolerated by thoſe that are call'd Chriſtians. And yet there are ſtill others as bad, or worſe than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their <hi>Spiritual Tyranny,</hi> in exacting
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49390:48"/>a blind <hi>Obedience</hi> in <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Faith;</hi> their innumerable <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions,</hi> which almoſt ſwallow up the whole Subſtance of <hi>Religion;</hi> their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>Schiſm</hi> (many degrees worſe than that of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>) in <hi>ſeparating</hi> from all other <hi>Churches,</hi> far more Pure and Orthodox than themſelves; and yet, becauſe they cannot be the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Subjects,</hi> therefore they ſhall be none of <hi>Chriſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſay nothing of their <hi>School Points</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſtical Divinity,</hi> 'tis evident that their whole <hi>Religion</hi> is only the bare ſhadow and outſides of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and meer <hi>Pageantry</hi> and <hi>Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of <hi>Devotion:</hi> For alaſs! their poor ſimple and ignorant <hi>Laity,</hi> ſay, hear, and do they know not what, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from their Churches as void of Inſtruction, and Chriſtian Admonition and Edification, as when they went; and yet for all this, (which is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt aggravation of their Sin and Miſery,) they are obliged to believe, that this their blind <hi>Devotion</hi> is not only <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> but <hi>meritorious.</hi> Beſides, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49390:48"/>notorious and damnable <hi>Sins</hi> paſs for <hi>Venial,</hi> and how eaſily are they atton'd for? Inſomuch that a few <hi>Drops</hi> of <hi>Holy Water,</hi> and <hi>Croſs</hi> upon their <hi>Breaſts</hi> or <hi>Foreheads,</hi> will throughly waſh off the <hi>Stain,</hi> (according to their groundleſs Apprehenſions,) and expiate the guilt of all their heinous and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sins.</hi> Their notorious <hi>Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> have ſcarce left any room for Truth, whereby they deceive others, and offer violence to their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. But tho poor ignorant and unwary Souls may be impoſed upon and deluded, yet it cannot be ſo with an All-ſeeing God; who will one day convince all Men, and expoſe their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtical <hi>Villanies</hi> and <hi>Reſervations</hi> to the open and publick view both of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this Liberty and Indulgence of theirs is ſo pleaſing and acceptable to ſenſual and carnal <hi>Men,</hi> that 'tis no great wonder that they gain ſo many Proſelytes to their Party, as ſome do preſumptuouſly and vainly boaſt. But then if we give our ſelves the trouble
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49390:49"/>to enquire what ſort of Perſons they are whom they have perverted; we ſhall find, that many of 'em are ſilly Women and Men notoriouſly debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ignorant, or of mercenary Spirits, who expect <hi>Preferment</hi> in that Way. And therefore we have no great cauſe to regret the loſs of them; and if our number be leſs, yet we are not the worſe: For if all our Licentious <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> and <hi>Malefactors,</hi> who are not worthy to live in the World, ſhould go over to their Communion, we ſhall have no great cauſe to complain.</p>
               <p>But alas! theſe erroneous <hi>Principles</hi> and worſe <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who being the more intelligent and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort of that Communion, cannot be ſo much the error and miſtake of their Judgments, as the perverſeneſs of their Wills: And tho a ſimple and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Popeling,</hi> who lies under ſuch Temptations and Obligations, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) may be ſaved; yet I am afraid, the more Learned and Diſcreet having made Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience, are in a very dangerous
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49390:49"/>State, if they live and die according to thoſe corrupt Principles; becauſe they are in the number of thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Hereſies</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks of.</p>
               <p>What I have already offer'd, are <hi>Truths</hi> as clear as the Sun; nor can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in the World be more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative</hi> to a <hi>Perſon</hi> throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi> And yet for all this, 'tis a thouſand to one you'l meet with ſome bold and cunning <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> who'l tell you a great many plauſible <hi>Stories,</hi> and endeavour to elude the moſt clear and convincing <hi>Reaſons,</hi> which can be urg'd againſt them; whereby they do ſtrangely impoſe upon, and many times entrap poor ignorant and unwary <hi>Souls.</hi> To inſtance in ſome <hi>Particulars:</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, A <hi>Catholick</hi> (ſay they,) ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dying, even by the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves, may be ſaved. [Which is a confeſſed Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Moderation.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the <hi>One Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is more likely to be found in all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49390:50"/>
                  <hi>World,</hi> than in a <hi>Corner.</hi> [As if there were no true Church in the World, but theirs.]</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In all Ages than of later Years. [Not conſidering that we had a Chriſtian Church in <hi>England,</hi> before ever <hi>Popery</hi> was known in the World.]</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That this <hi>One Church</hi> is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be found in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> than in <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</hi> [Which we could eaſily recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and retort upon themſelves: For there are more and greater <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> than in any other <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.]</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That they have a <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> from the Days of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> downward. [So have we, as is fully evident from all our Antient and Authentick <hi>Records.</hi> See Biſhop <hi>Bamhal</hi>'s Account of the <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And they have quite forgotten that there were three <hi>Popes,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> at the ſame time: What then became of their uninterrupted Succeſſion?</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49390:50"/>
               <p>Sixthly, That the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Supreme Head</hi> of the <hi>Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal,</hi> and <hi>Chriſts Vicar</hi> in extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary upon <hi>Earth.</hi> [Which ſpurious <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> (as we noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) is rejected by at leaſt two parts of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> at this day, and diſliked by ſome <hi>National Churches</hi> (as 'tis ſuppoſed) of their own Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who are inclinable enough (if they knew but how) to caſt off that Papal and Tyrannical Yoke.]</p>
               <p>Seventhly, That the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is only a Branch lopt off, or a Rag torn from the <hi>Coat,</hi> and that we had no <hi>Church</hi> nor <hi>Religion</hi> before <hi>Luther.</hi> [This is a moſt groſs and manifeſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth:</hi> For we had a <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> in <hi>England</hi> before ever St. <hi>Peter</hi> came at <hi>Rome,</hi> founded by <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> and flouriſhed under King <hi>Lucius,</hi> the firſt <hi>Chriſtian Monarch</hi> in the World. And we know very well by what <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations</hi> and <hi>Encroachments,</hi> and the time when <hi>Popery</hi> firſt got footing in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> that <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk,</hi> cauſed ſome hundreds of that Order to be ſlain
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49390:51"/>at <hi>Bangor,</hi> to make way for it: And 'tis further evident by what Means and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> did work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Weakneſſes and Credulity of ſome, and the Neceſſities of others of our <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> not having the Power, or Courage, or Reſolution, to caſt off the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> till the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, King of <hi>England:</hi> A Perſon whoſe <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Affairs</hi> (let our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> beſpatter him as they pleaſe,) made him a fit <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> to begin the <hi>Reformation;</hi> which thro' God's <hi>Providence,</hi> and the prudent and religious Conduct of his <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> has been happily carried on and perfected; which we hope thro' the Favour and Protection of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty who now Reigns, may be continued a Bleſſing to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> and our <hi>Poſterity.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Hence therefore 'twill appear to you, That theſe are all thred-bare and ſtale <hi>Evaſions</hi> and <hi>Subterſuges,</hi> to colour and palliate their groundleſs and unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pretences to <hi>Antiquity, Viſibility, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Magnificence,</hi> Right of <hi>Succeſſion</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49390:51"/>of, and in their Church: All which have been anſwered at leaſt an hundred times, by Worthy and Learned <hi>Authors,</hi> as you'l ſee afterwards. But this <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> has been ſo well ſtated and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly canvaſſed by our <hi>Church of England Men</hi> in theſe laſt three Years, that there will be more difficulty now than ever, to perſuade any Gentleman of Senſe and Ingenuity to believe their incongruous and hateful Abſurdities.</p>
               <p>But yet there are ſome others of the ſame Foot-mark, who having laid aſide all Modeſty and Candour, their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads are ſo ſteel'd with Confidence, as to affirm, That we have neither <hi>Church, Prieſts, Sacraments,</hi> nor <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> amongſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> and are ſo uncharitable as to load <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> with all the nonſenſical and unjuſt Calumnies imaginable, not regarding what they are, ſo they be but ſpiteful and malicious; obſerving the old Maxim, <hi>Fortiter calumniari aliquid haerebit.</hi> Nay, they'l even diſclaim their own <hi>Popiſh Doctrins</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> as the <hi>Invocation of Saints, Worſhiping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> &amp;c. and do tell the credulous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49390:52"/>that their Adverſaries out of meer Spight and Malice, do miſrepreſent them.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Methods</hi> have been lately uſed (by an Eminent Papiſt here of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Neighborhood,) to ſome Perſons of our <hi>Communion</hi> who were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly my Pariſhioners, and ſeem'd to be warping towards <hi>Popery:</hi> They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me with it, and look'd upon thoſe <hi>Sophiſms</hi> to be nervous and ſtrong Arguments and Motives, (and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were if they had been true,) to perſuade them to change their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. But ſuch ſhuffling Tricks as theſe carry their own Confutation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them; for this is an old piece of <hi>Legerdemain,</hi> which one would have thought ſhould have been long ſince exploded. And I find the very ſame <hi>Hocus pocus,</hi> Illuſions, uſed by the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts,</hi> about the beginning of the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> For we know very well, what Priviledges are allow'd them to ſwear and forſwear; and not only deny, but even rail againſt their own received <hi>Doctrins, Practices, Church,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49390:52"/>and the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, for the Intereſt of the <hi>Catholick (i. e.)</hi> the <hi>Roman Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Conſult Dr. <hi>Nalſon</hi>'s <hi>Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> and there you'l find many of their jugling Devices, and being Men of Latitude and Faculties to prepare Diſhes for every Palate.</p>
               <p>I have been a little more expreſs in ſtating theſe <hi>Differences,</hi> becauſe I know thoſe <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries</hi> are crept into all Countreys, and do every where lie in wait to debauch and corrupt Young Gentlemen, both in their <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Manners.</hi> There are not a few Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of both, who have been taken Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives by them: I ſhall name Two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. The one a Perſon of good <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> ſtrong and quick natural <hi>Parts,</hi> an excellent <hi>Scholar,</hi> under the Conduct (as 'twas ſuppoſed,) of a well qualified <hi>Tutor,</hi> well educated according to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> by his pious and prudent Parents; and yet for all this, was perverted in his <hi>Travels,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues a zealous and cunning <hi>Papiſt.</hi> There was another Gentleman alſo, both of my Acquaintance, not inferior to the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49390:53"/>former, and every way as well fitted for Travel, yet did contract ſuch a habit of <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> and <hi>Debauchery,</hi> (to ſay no worſe,) that in few years an <hi>Eſtate</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 2000 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> is intirely waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and nothing remains but a bare puff of Honour without any Eſtate to ſupport it: I could tell you all the particulars by what Methods that unfortunate, ſweet, and ingenuous Young Gentleman was allured and trapan'd into theſe <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> who alſo died immaturely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which <hi>Examples</hi> amongſt many others, have been often in my Thoughts: And tho there be not the leaſt grounds of any Jealouſie or Suſpition of your Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, yet I have ſet them in your View as Land Marks, and Sea Marks, to prevent the danger of ſplitting your Veſſel, (ſo well built and richly laden,) either upon the Sands and Shelves of <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> or the Rocks and Splinters of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore (Dear Sir) let me beſeech you once more to be continually upon your Watch, that you may return with the ſame Soul and ſame Body you car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49390:53"/>from hence, and all the Tempers and Diſpoſitions of both. And for this End endeavor throughly to underſtand, and then live up to the Principles and Rules of that Religion you have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to profeſs'd. This will prove the beſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt that deſtructive <hi>Poiſon,</hi> which might otherwiſe taint and infect both your <hi>Intellectuals</hi> and <hi>Morals;</hi> and not only deſtroy the Chriſtian, but even the Man (or rational part) within you.</p>
               <p>Let me adviſe you ſtill more <hi>particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> not ſo much as to lend an <hi>Ear</hi> to hear, nor a <hi>Tongue</hi> to diſcourſe with thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting <hi>Syrens;</hi> be afraid of their ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Favours, whoſe Errand is Deceit, and under the pretence of Kindneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, will wound you to the very Heart. Look not upon the pompous Ceremonies and coſtly Ornaments of that <hi>Religion</hi> wherein all things are outwardly glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and pleaſant to the Eye; but keep cloſe to innocent Truth, and let your <hi>Soul</hi> be always deeply affected with that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip whoſe Majeſty is in the Heart, not in the Face, which we profeſs (with the greateſt comfort and ſatisfaction, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49390:54"/>may we ever do ſo) in the Communion of the beſt of <hi>Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen at length that the <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> wherein they differ from Us, are <hi>Fundamental Points</hi> both of Faith and Worſhip: Therefore have no communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with thoſe of that Way, unleſs it be where civil <hi>Relations,</hi> and <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> require your compliance.</p>
               <p>Now, to conclude this Point, all the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are called <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> a Name common to Us with our <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> beyond Sea, and ſo indeed we are: <q rend="inline">For we do ſolemnly proteſt againſt the Popiſh Univerſal Hierarchy, Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judgment, Diſpenſations with the Laws of God and Sins of Men, Oral Traditions and other Sacriledges, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Kingdoms, depoſing and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Princes, the Merit of Good Works in our Converſion, the Prieſts pretended Power of tranſubſtantiating Bread and Wine into the Body and Blood of Chriſt, the Sacrifice of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49390:54"/>Maſs, Adoration of the Hoſtie, Images, Relicks, Prayers to Saints and Angels, Power of Indulgences, Doctrin of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, neceſſity of Auricular Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Prohibition of Prieſts Marriages, Pilgrimages, Prayers in an unknown Tongue, multitude of Sacraments, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Miracles and <hi>Indian</hi> Wonders, and pretences of curing the Deaf Dumb, Blind, Lame, and raiſing the Dead, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, mental Reſervations, pious Frauds, legendary Fables, deviliſh Incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſacred, yet diabolical Magick, and all their other Deluſions and Fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, as damnable and anti-chriſtian.</q> You'l be pleaſed (Sir) to join with me in this <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> (the very naming whereof, tho I cannot now inſiſt upon all the Particulars, might almoſt induce you to it,) and let all true hearted and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> both here and every where, ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are alſo ſeveral other <hi>Religious Sects</hi> (or rather Hereticks,) which do err from the <hi>Foundation</hi> and the true <hi>Faith:</hi> Such are the <hi>Anti-Trinitarians, Arians, Socinians,</hi> &amp;c. who deny the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49390:55"/>
                  <hi>Doctrin</hi> of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and our <hi>Saviours Satisfaction:</hi> All which being excommunicated by Us, you muſt avoid them as the Peſts, and Enemies of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and have no Intercourſe nor Communion with them.</p>
               <p>There's another ſilly <hi>Sect</hi> called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> a People ſo far fallen from <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> that they do ſcarce retain any one <hi>Article</hi> of the true <hi>Faith,</hi> ſlight and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject all the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and extol the <hi>Light within them</hi> above the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> as the only ſufficient <hi>Rule</hi> they are obliged to walk by. I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell you in ſhort, what <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> is, and ſhall need to ſay no more of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there's ſo little <hi>Temptation</hi> to that <hi>Opinion.</hi> Thus much by way of Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. My method leads me,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, To conſider thoſe <hi>Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Arguments,</hi> which our <hi>Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Non-conformity</hi> have urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in defence of their Separation from Us. But to do them all the <hi>Juſtice</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, I muſt note to you in the firſt place, That thoſe called <hi>Antinomians,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49390:55"/>Anabaptiſts, Independants,</hi> and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> do hold the Foundation, tho they differ from Us in ſome Opinions not eſſential to Salvation; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their uncharitableneſs to Us, we account them <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> as holding the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> tho they build upon a weak Foundation.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing <hi>Providence</hi> has led you into thoſe Countries for the preſent, where you cannot worſhip God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your own Way; the <hi>Church of England,</hi> both in her <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,</hi> allows you to communicate with thoſe Siſter-Churches of the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to whom we have always given the right Hand of Fellowſhip, tho there be ſome circumſtantial Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Them and Us. But,</p>
               <p>You'l probably meet with ſome in your <hi>Travels,</hi> as well as in our own <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> who will be very forward to find Faults with and cenſure our <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> (as we have many of that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricious Humour amongſt Us, tho they ſcarce underſtand it. Therefore for the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49390:56"/>further Confirmation and Eſtabliſhment of your own Judgment herein, and that you may be better fortified with <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> to vindicate our <hi>Church,</hi> and clear thoſe <hi>Objections</hi> which may be urged againſt her. We ſhall conſider,</p>
               <p>Firſt, The moſt material <hi>Objections,</hi> which have been formed againſt our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> and <hi>Church Politie,</hi> both at home and abroad.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We ſhall draw ſome ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Inferences</hi> from thoſe <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions,</hi> for your further ſatisfaction. And,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Lay down ſome <hi>Rules</hi> by way of <hi>caution,</hi> which I hope may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you, and by your Influence, many others from a groundleſs <hi>Separation.</hi> Of theſe diſtinctly: And,</p>
               <p>Firſt, All the Scruples of our <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Brethren,</hi> againſt our <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Set Form of Worſhip,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to, and comprehended under theſe two <hi>Objections.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They charge Us with <hi>Popery,</hi> (which we abhor as much, if not more than they do,) becauſe (ſay they) our <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49390:56"/>is taken out of the <hi>Popiſh Maſs-Book,</hi> that they are <hi>Popiſh Prayers;</hi> and much of our <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and many of our <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are now uſed in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which <hi>Objection</hi> at the firſt appearance, ſeems to be very harſh; and has ſo affrighted ſome weak, yet well-meaning <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that they dare ſcarce come near Us, but hold off, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from our <hi>Communion.</hi> To which I</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This <hi>Objection</hi> is ſo far from being of any force againſt Us, that it do's very much approve and juſtifie the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Moderation</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as moſt willing and deſirous to communicate with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in all Things wherein we can do it lawfully, and with a ſafe Conſcience. Beſides, thoſe <hi>Divines</hi> who compiled our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> were all Men of extraordinary Parts, Piety and Learning, and ſeveral of them died <hi>Martyrs</hi> for our <hi>Religion.</hi> Nor have our <hi>diſſenting Brethren</hi> the leaſt colour of Reaſon to brand our <hi>Church Service</hi> with ſavouring too much of <hi>Popery,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Papiſts</hi> always have, and ever had our <hi>Worſhip</hi> in the greateſt deteſtation
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49390:57"/>and abhorrence; becauſe they know 'tis impoſſible that <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould ever return upon Us, or be eſtabliſht again in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> while our <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> is kept unaltered.</p>
               <p>For, the whole Form of our <hi>Worſhip</hi> is point blank contrary to <hi>Image-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> praying to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice, Doctrin</hi> of their <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> &amp;c. And this is the true Reaſon why they do ſo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally hate both <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> and our <hi>Religion.</hi> And again, thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> in our <hi>Liturgy</hi> which were taken out of the <hi>Maſs-Book,</hi> are many of them the <hi>Collects</hi> and <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the Antient <hi>Fathers,</hi> which were in uſe before ever <hi>Popery</hi> was known in the World; which being purged from the <hi>Popiſh Superſtition</hi> by our <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> are now lawfully uſed by the <hi>Church of England,</hi> according to their <hi>Original Inſtitution:</hi> Inſomuch, that thoſe who cavil at our Service, becauſe ſome part of it is uſed by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> may as well find fault with the <hi>Epiſtles and Goſpels, Pſalms, Chapters, Creeds, Commandments, Lords Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. theſe being alſo in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49390:57"/>the Papiſts <hi>Maſs-Book.</hi> Having fully cleared this firſt <hi>Objection,</hi> we paſs to the</p>
               <p n="2">2. And they charge Us again with many <hi>Corruptions, Additions, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi> and circumſtantial <hi>Errors</hi> in our <hi>Set Form of Worſhip and Diſcipline,</hi> (for they have no Objections againſt our Doctrin and Fundamentals;) and for thoſe ſeeming Reaſons, they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to withdraw and ſeparate from our <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This may ſeem to be a weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Objection</hi> at the firſt ſight, and the moſt plead it (being joined with the former, which we have anſwered to the full,) as the Cauſe, why they think and ſpeak ſo hardly of our Church, and deſert our Communion: But they might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to alter their Opinion, if (laying aſide all <hi>Prejudice,</hi>) they would but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and impartially conſider theſe few Things. And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis a true and undoubted <hi>Maxim,</hi> that all Perſons are obliged to hold <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with the National and Eſtabliſh'd <hi>Church</hi> where they live, and muſt by no means ſeparate from it; tho there be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49390:58"/>ſome circumſtantial <hi>Additions, Errors</hi> and <hi>Defects,</hi> in its external <hi>Worſhip, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> For 'tis plain, that the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> did not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from, but held Communion with the <hi>Jews</hi> in their <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> tho there were very many and great Defects and Corruptions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both in their <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Practice.</hi> This is clear in many <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances:</hi> For the ſolemn <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> were for a long time a-wanting; and ſuch <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> were ſet up, as not only the People thereby became ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and immoral, but even the Prieſts alſo (as <hi>Eli</hi>'s two Sons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) brought a Scandal upon their <hi>Religion.</hi> Were not theſe greater Faults than any of our fierceſt Adverſaries can charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us? And yet for all that, we ſind not one Preſident of ſo much as any ſingle Perſon that departed from their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At the time of our B. <hi>Saviours</hi> coming into the World, the <hi>Jewiſh Worſhip</hi> was exceedingly corrupted with the <hi>Leaven</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> &amp; the <hi>Hereſie</hi> of the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces,</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49390:58"/>who denied the Immortality of the Soul and the Reſurrection of the Body. Beſides, the whole <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God</hi> was intolerably prophaned, the <hi>Temple</hi> pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, <hi>Religion</hi> ſubverted, <hi>Judgment</hi> and the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> trampled upon and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, many needleſs and ſuperſtitious <hi>Ceremonies</hi> interlarded with their <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>People.</hi> addicted to all manner of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and even the <hi>Prieſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very heterodox and diſſolute both in their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners:</hi> And yet at that time, we find ſeveral religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both Men and Women, with great Zeal and Devotion, worſhiping God in the Temple, as <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Simeon, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c. And our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf was (by his pious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) preſented in the Temple according to the Cuſtom and Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> He af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards kept the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and all the <hi>Feſtivals</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> frequented and taught daily in the <hi>Temple</hi> &amp; in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> gave <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reverence,</hi> and paid <hi>Tribute</hi> to their <hi>Rulers;</hi> nor did he ever deſert their Communion, till he was forced to retire to ſave his own Life:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49390:59"/>So that he thought it neceſſary (and ſo did thoſe other Votaries) to join in Gods <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> notwithſtanding thoſe great <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Defects,</hi> which thanks be to God, are not chargeable upon Us. But,</p>
               <p n="3">3. There were many Errors and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, both in the <hi>Doctrin</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the then ſlouriſhing <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> &amp;c. and yet the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo far from encouraging a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in, and <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Communion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Churches;</hi> that he threatens thoſe Perſons with the ſevereſt Puniſhments, who were the Inſtruments in fomenting and promoting thoſe <hi>Animoſities</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</hi> Nor is there any one <hi>Inſtance</hi> or <hi>Preſident</hi> in the whole <hi>Scripture,</hi> to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant our departure from any Church that is Sound and Orthodox in her <hi>Principles,</hi> however erroneous and corrupt in the <hi>Politie</hi> and <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip.</hi> We might hereunto add,</p>
               <p n="4">4. The concurrent <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions</hi> of the moſt Eminent and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Divines</hi> beyond Sea; who have unanimouſly declared their Diſlike of a Separation from our <hi>Communion;</hi> as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49390:59"/>Bullinger, Bucer,</hi> and many others. And tho they diſſented from Us in leſſer Things, yet held Communion and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with our <hi>Church</hi> &amp; <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> as may appear by their ſeveral <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to our <hi>Reformers;</hi> and would have been glad if their Circumſtances would have allowed our Form of <hi>Church Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie;</hi> and deſervedly preferr'd it to any <hi>Church Government</hi> in the World. But to argue yet more cloſely;</p>
               <p n="5">5. If any will refuſe our <hi>Communion,</hi> and ſeparate from Us, becauſe there are ſome pretended Errors in the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Circumſtantials</hi> of our <hi>Worſhip,</hi> (which yet none have ever been able to prove againſt Us,) they'l be obliged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſcore, to withdraw their <hi>Communion</hi> from all the <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom:</hi> For what <hi>Church Government</hi> ſhall they be ever able to aſſign, that's ſo pure and ſincere, as to be wholly exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Circumſtantial Errors</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects?</hi> And were there not more Faults in the Worſhip of the <hi>Primitive Churches</hi> for the five firſt <hi>Centuries,</hi> than are at preſent in Ours? Are there no Errors in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49390:60"/>the <hi>Worſhip, Conſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Government</hi> of <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi> I'm ſure many of their Learned <hi>Divines</hi> have ingenuouſly acknowledg'd that all things were not according to their Deſire, and yet did not think it Prudence to alter the Government for the ſake of ſome ſmall Errors.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> muſt either diſclaim theſe <hi>Conceits,</hi> or turn <hi>Hermits</hi> and <hi>Anchorets,</hi> live in a <hi>Cell</hi> or <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and even depart from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; who (as I could eaſily ſhew them) are guilty of as many, if not more, and greater Faults and Errors in their little Aſſemblies, than can be juſtly charged upon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> or the <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Whither would not theſe wild and extravagant Fancies carry any Man that ſhall give way to them? So that they muſt either prove their own Churches to be infallible in point of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> which I think the moſt of them diſclaim, or for ever quit their <hi>Pretenſions</hi> for a <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from Us, becauſe of the little Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which they have diſcovered in our <hi>Adminiſtrations.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:49390:60"/>
               <p>Having thus fully anſwer'd the chief <hi>Objections</hi> of our Brethren for their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which I know will fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you. We ſhall proceed,</p>
               <p>Secondly, To draw ſome clear and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable <hi>Inferences</hi> from the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> for the prevention of all further <hi>Scruples</hi> in this Caſe. And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It would be a ſtrange Deluſion, and no leſs than abſolute <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> to caſt off all the <hi>Publick Ordinances,</hi> or neglect the <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Solemn Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe ſome things may be diſliked, or excepted againſt in their <hi>Adminiſtrations</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The greateſt Honour we can aſcribe to God, is to worſhip ſolemnly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly in the <hi>Publick Aſſemblies</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> And therefore it muſt be the moſt heinous Crime to make a Schiſm and Rent in any particular <hi>Church,</hi> where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is effectually preſent by his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> Nor can any one have a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>Plea,</hi> to withdraw from the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ordinances</hi> in any <hi>Nation,</hi> till <hi>Chriſt</hi> has deſerted them; which no Man can object againſt the <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49390:61"/>Church of England:</hi> Wherein (as before) the whole World will acknowledge, that the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is purely preach'd, and the <hi>Sacraments</hi> duly adminiſtred in that admirable <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which is ſcarce to be parallel'd in any <hi>National Church</hi> upon <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, thoſe who are ſo ſtrait laced as to require abſolute Perfection in the Adminiſtration of <hi>Divine Offices</hi> and <hi>Church Government,</hi> muſt be guilty of that <hi>Popiſh Error,</hi> in confining the <hi>Church,</hi> with all its <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities,</hi> to their own <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>Party;</hi> and ſo caſt off a conſiderable <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> (as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is at this Day,) which profeſſes and practiſes all the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip.</hi> Hence we alſo infer,</p>
               <p n="3">3. That many great and unavoidable <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> do always attend a wilful and unlawful <hi>Separation:</hi> For a <hi>Sciſſure</hi> in and departure from a <hi>True Church,</hi> (as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is, and none of our ſevereſt <hi>Adverſaries</hi> can deny,) is moſt diſhonourable and diſpleaſing to <hi>God,</hi> a ſcandal to <hi>Religion,</hi> hinders the Succeſs
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49390:61"/>of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> opens a wide Gap to <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs, Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> and is a diſmal <hi>Preſage</hi> of the removing of our <hi>Candleſtick,</hi> Mat. 12.25. Why then ſhould any Perſons withdraw and ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the <hi>Communion</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> for the ſake of a few <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar,</hi> and hereby put an Opportunity into the Adverſaries hands, to ruin both us and themſelves? But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Tho all Perſons in this Nation are obliged to hold <hi>Communion</hi> with the <hi>Church of England,</hi> (ſeeing thoſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Defects in her are only modal and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial, which no <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> can be free from in this State of Tryal and Probation,) yet we are ſorbidden to communicate with any <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Sin:</hi> And this is the true reaſon and ground of forſaking the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> becauſe her <hi>Errors</hi> are <hi>Fundamental,</hi> (as we have ſeen already,) and the Conditions of <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with her ſuch, as we cannot comply with, unleſs we offer Violence to our own <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And we do always ſolemnly declare, that if their New <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and unchriſtian <hi>Practices</hi> did not hinder Us, we ſhould moſt freely
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49390:62"/>and chearfully communicate with her; nor do we further depart from her, than ſhe departs from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and her <hi>Self,</hi> as to her antient <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And again, we have ſo much Love and Charity for our <hi>modern Diſſenters</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that if any one has a truly tender Conſcience, ſo as after a diligent and faithful uſe of all convenient and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> for his Conviction, (as earneſt Prayer to God, reading of good Books, conſultation with his Pariſh-Miniſter, or ſome other Pious and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he ſtill remains ſcrupulous and unſatisfied; yet rather than ſin againſt his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, we do not blame, but pity him, if he modeſtly withdraws from our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. But I am afraid there are ſome who have not practiſed theſe Methods, altho I have the Charity to believe that very many have; and that moſt of thoſe who have ſeparated from our <hi>Communion,</hi> have not done it through a wilful Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, but meerly upon the account of Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our Brethren of the Non-conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty might do well to conſider alſo, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49390:62"/>none gains any thing by a groundleſs <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Separation,</hi> but that ſort of Men whoſe chief Maxim to promote their own Ends, hath always been, <hi>Divide &amp; impera:</hi> For 'tis very obſervable that the Intereſt of the Reform'd Religion is daily weaken'd by our unchriſtian and inteſtine Diviſions. And 'tis very certain, that we cannot do our Enemies greater Service nor more precipitate our own Ruine, than by crumbling our ſelves into <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Parties:</hi> Inſomuch, that I am afraid, that thoſe who now ſeparate from Us, and (in this juncture) forſake our Communion, will one day find and feel to their great coſt (not to mention the preſent <hi>Miſchiefs</hi>) that it were a thouſand times better to ſwallow an innocent <hi>Ceremony</hi> than rend a <hi>Church;</hi> ſeeing the greateſt Sins ſhall have a lighter Puniſhment than <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Separation. For the Eye that mocketh his Father, and deſpiſeth the Garment of his Mother, the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pluck it out, and the young Eagles devour it.</hi> See further upon the Miſchiefs of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> Dr. <hi>Falkners Libertas Eccleſ.</hi> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Which brings me to the,</p>
               <p>Third and laſt thing, Which will be to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49390:63"/>lay down ſome <hi>Rules</hi> by way of <hi>Caution</hi> and <hi>Advice,</hi> which may ſecure you, and by your <hi>Influence,</hi> many others from a groundleſs <hi>Separation.</hi> And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt be ſubject to every <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of <hi>Man for the Lords ſake:</hi> For they are Gods Miniſters, and the ſupreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of theſe Kingdoms is inveſted with Sovereign Power and Authority to order and adminiſter the Affairs of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, for the peace and benefit of Mens Souls, as well as their Bodies and Eſtates: Nor can this ſeem ſtrange to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one, who either underſtands the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory:</hi> For 'tis plain, that the religious Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as King <hi>David, Solomon, Aſa Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat, Hezekiah,</hi> &amp;c. and all the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Emperors,</hi> as <hi>Conſtantine the Great</hi> and his <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> (till the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Uſurpation,) were as much concern'd in ordering of the Affairs of the Church, as the Adminiſtration of Civil Government. And indeed, unleſs this Power and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty were allow'd to the Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, he ſhould be unable to provide for the benefit of his Subjects; nor could there be any ſuch thing as <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49390:63"/>in the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws</hi> being only <hi>Bruta fulmina</hi> without the concurrence and enforcement of the Civil Power: So that from hence it muſt needs follow, that a cheerful Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to and a hearty Compliance with all the Laws and Conſtitutions of our admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Government, both in Church and State, is abſolutely neceſſary, not only for our own ſakes, but the Peace and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the whole Body.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis a ſtrange Miſtake then which ſome have run upon, that nothing is to be admitted in our <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Politie</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> but what is <hi>plainly expreſt in the Holy Scriptures;</hi> hereby excluding all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> in Matters and Things indiſſerent. Which wild <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis</hi> has been the Original of all thoſe untenable <hi>Opinions</hi> now on foot; and the very moſt of our <hi>unchriſtian Diviſions,</hi> which have almoſt torn in pieces our Church, are owing to this unreaſonable and groundleſs <hi>Conjecture:</hi> Whereas on the contrary, the Writers of the greateſt Note and Eminence amongſt our Brethren of the Non-conformity, are forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49390:64"/>that there are many <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> in the <hi>Public Service of God,</hi> and the <hi>Government of the Church,</hi> which muſt be regulated and order'd according to the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Prudence;</hi> as the holy Apoſtle directs in thoſe general Rules, <hi>Let all things be done decently in order, and for Edification.</hi> And do alſo confeſs, that even in their own Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies (and we know it to be true and certain,) there are many ſuch <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> for which they have no <hi>expreſs Rule</hi> in Scripture; but do uſe them <hi>prudentially</hi> for the Honour and Intereſt of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Order &amp; Uniformity of Gods <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, 'tis obſervable that the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> treat chiefly of the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and only mention the <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> with ſome general Rules (as before) for the ordering of its <hi>Politie</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline:</hi> Inſomuch, that <hi>many Perſons of great Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Judgment</hi> are of opinion, that there's no one <hi>Set-Form of Government</hi> for the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> to be found in the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> but muſt be left to our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours to order and appoint according to the Rules and Dictates of ſound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49390:64"/>and Diſcretion: Which the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> gives a moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Account of in his <hi>Eccleſiaſt. Polit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor can this in the leaſt impeach (as ſome have vainly objected the Sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> or the Fidelity of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in not leaving a perfect <hi>Model</hi> of <hi>Church Government</hi> behind him: For we have ſeen already, that the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> were primarily intended to inſtruct us in the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Morality,</hi> and ſpeak only overtly of <hi>Church Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi> And, for the Fidelity of <hi>Chriſt</hi> herein, 'tis plain that the Church in our Saviours Time was in her <hi>Minority,</hi> which muſt after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (by degrees) grow up to a ſtate of greater <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Perfection.</hi> What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have urged from the Form of <hi>Church Government</hi> under the <hi>Jewiſh Oeconomie</hi> concludes nothing: For the <hi>Jews</hi> lived all under one <hi>Politie</hi> and in one <hi>Nation;</hi> whereas <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is diſperſed all over the World, under many diſſerent <hi>Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of Religious <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> muſt be ſuited to the State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of different People within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49390:65"/>Juriſdictions, as may appear moſt juſt and reaſonable to the Judgments and Diſcretion of their lawful Governours. Therefore,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Tho every Perſon be obliged to hate and flie from Idolatry, Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet none ſhould be affrighted from his Duty with meer <hi>Buggs</hi> and <hi>Scar-crows,</hi> or the empty Appearances of <hi>Error</hi> without ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Grounds. For tho our <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> have been extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cavil'd at by ſome of our Adverſaries, yet 'tis evident that neither the <hi>Prophets</hi> of old, nor our <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> nor the <hi>Primitive Fathers,</hi> did ever find fault with the Stated Methods and Forms of Prayer, but did practiſe and appoint 'em themſelves, and highly encourag'd them in others. For there are many <hi>Set-Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer, Benedictions</hi> and <hi>Thankſgivings,</hi> in the Writings of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our compoſed a <hi>Form of Prayer</hi> to be uſed by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> (tho they were doubtleſs as able to pray by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit as the moſt Seraphick <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi>) which <hi>Method</hi> alſo was obſerved by <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> for the direction and aſſiſtance of his <hi>Diſciples</hi> in God's <hi>Worſhip.</hi> All
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49390:65"/>which <hi>Stated Forms</hi> became Patterns and Preſidents to the Churches of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages, who had all their ſeveral <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> as we have; nor is there any thing in our <hi>Service Book</hi> which is contrary to, but moſt exactly conformable to thoſe <hi>Rules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Let not the bare Pretence then of ſome ſmall Errors in and about the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> prevail with any Man to ſeparate from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his <hi>National Church,</hi> ſeeing there have been, and are as many, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably greater Errors in all the Churches of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all Ages of the Goſpel: For tho our Bleſſed Saviour promis'd, <hi>that the Gates of Hell ſhould not prevail againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, that he will be with her to the end of the World, ſend his Spirit to lead her into all Truth, and abide with her for ever;</hi> yet theſe <hi>Promiſes</hi> do only reſpect the Fundamental Doctrins of the Catholic and Univerſal Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or a People profeſſing the Truth, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may err (as all of them do) in Opinions not eſſential to <hi>Religion.</hi> And ſeeing every particular Church may be guilty of ſome Errors and Miſtakes in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Circumſtances of Religion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49390:66"/>fore he that will ſeparate upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count can ſcarce hold Communion with any National Church upon Earth. And thoſe fickle and fanciful Perſons might have had the ſame <hi>Plea,</hi> to have ſeparated from the Chriſtian Church in the time of the Apoſtles that they have now from Us: Nor is there any one that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the State of our Church, but will readily acknowledge, that our Orders of <hi>Biſhops Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Set Form</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> are if not of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical,) yet of Primitive Inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="5">5. No meer Inconveniences, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Errors or Defects and thoſe only alledged, not proved againſt Us, can juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie or excuſe a <hi>Departure</hi> from Us, ſince I have made it fully evident that our Church holds and maintains all the <hi>Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials</hi> both of <hi>Faith</hi> and of <hi>Worſhip.</hi> For, we have ſeen already, that all Men are oblig'd to conform themſelves to the Conſtitutions of their National Church, tho ſome of the external Modes &amp; Forms be inconvenient, diſorderly and defective, rather than not be of any Church at all: And what they cannot reform without diſturbing the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi>) 'tis
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49390:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Duty to tolerate, ſeeing there's no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and Particular Church in the World, (as we have already obſerved) whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and Government are abſolutely perfect. Therefore,</p>
               <p n="6">6. Thoſe Perſons are extreamly to blame that require greater <hi>Purity</hi> in Gods <hi>Public Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> than the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> have command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or the Primitive Orthodox <hi>Fathers</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to Poſterity. And tho there were ſome things amiſs in the outward <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Government:</hi> Yet 'tis not the Province, nor in the power of private Men to reform <hi>Religion;</hi> this being wholly leſt to the prudent management of thoſe <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> whom the divine Providence has conſtituted and appointed to rule over Us. Wherefore that precipitant and raſh <hi>Zeal</hi> (which ſome miſcall <hi>Puty</hi>) will more diſturb the Peace of their own Conſciences, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the Intereſt of the Church, than their charitable and peaceable Compliance with thoſe ſeeming Error, and Defects, which they ſo much cavil at and complain of.</p>
               <p n="7">7. 'Tis the greateſt Argument then of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence and Indiſcretion, to run upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and real Evils, upon thoſe Fears and Jealouſies (which are meerly groundleſs) and only imagin'd to be ſo. Will any Man of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> dare to forſake Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ordinances, and make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe perhaps there may
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49390:67"/>be ſome probable <hi>Defects</hi> in her <hi>Communion.</hi> For Gods Commands to attend his Publick Worſhip, and endeavour the Peace of the Church, are plain and poſitive, whereas the <hi>Errors</hi> objected againſt us are dubious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable: And now, to caſt the <hi>Scales,</hi> the far greater number of pious, learned &amp; judicious <hi>Men</hi> are on our <hi>ſide;</hi> ſo, that for any thing they know, they may be miſtaken. But granting 'em that we do err, let our <hi>Governours</hi> ſee to it, we have a ſufficient Rule for our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, (nor dare we ſubſtract it for the ſake of an Inconvenience only, if their <hi>Commands</hi> be not ſinful) but they have none for their Diſobedience. And therefore ſeeing they have no lawful Authority to reform the leaſt Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Miſtake in Government, it would be the greater Prudence, and more Chriſtian like to pray &amp; mourn in ſecret for what they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend amiſs, than to diſobey and exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their Governours, ſtir up Diviſions in the Church, &amp; run upon the dangerous <hi>Hazzards</hi> of a licentious and unwarrantable <hi>Separation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. We ſhould be always more concern'd for promoting the Intereſt of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and our own <hi>National Church,</hi> than the gratifying of our own perſonal and private <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Opinions.</hi> For it has been a great fault in moſt of our Brethren of the Non-conformity, who have been ſo wedded to their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Humours and Conceits, that they have almoſt quite forgot the <hi>Peace of the Church,</hi> and the true <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Reform'd
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49390:67"/>Religion.</hi> Hence have ſprung thoſe <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms,</hi> and that <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> which have ſo ſtrangely over-ſpread the whole Nation, to the great ſcandal of our Religion and Government; and have done what in their power lies to yield up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and us a Prey to our cruel and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Enemies. Whereas, if they had the leaſt ſenſe of their Duty and Intereſt, they would keep cloſe (at this Time eſpecially) to our <hi>Communion;</hi> which under God would be their chief Refuge, and yield in ſome ſmall Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, tho leſs agreeable to their own private Sentiments and Opinions, for the greater Benefit of the Publick.</p>
               <p n="9">9. No <hi>Prejudice</hi> ſhould prevail with any Man ſo far, as to make him unwilling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and diſclaim his <hi>Errors</hi> upon a through Conviction, and return to the ways of Truth and Peace, from which he has formerly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And therefore 'tis a great Fault in many who are unwilling to retract thoſe Errors which they have eſpouſed, leſt they ſhould be cenſured by their <hi>Party</hi> as <hi>Renegadoes</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates</hi> from their <hi>Religion:</hi> Whereas, if they would but ſeriouſly conſider it, 'twill be their greateſt Honour as well as Intereſt, and a ſpecial Evidence of their Integrity, to acknowledg &amp; recant their <hi>Errors</hi> &amp; <hi>Miſtakes;</hi> nor need any Man be aſham'd or afraid to confeſs he has erred. St. <hi>Aug.</hi> writ a whole Book of <hi>Retractations,</hi> for which he was deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly as much eſteem'd, as for any of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49390:68"/>Works: Nor can any Man come under the vile imputation and ſcandal of an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> who changes only ſome miſtaken Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Opinions, not his <hi>Religion.</hi> And</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Others have been extreamly to blame in ſetting up their own private Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Interpretations of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> as infallible <hi>Maxims</hi> and neceſſary <hi>Concluſions,</hi> inſomuch that they I rather diſturb the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Community,</hi> than be perſuaded to recede from them: For being ignorant of the ſcope and meaning of thoſe ſacred and lively <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> they preſently ſancy without the leaſt true ground, that every <hi>Paſſage</hi> founding that Way, muſt be a ſtrong and forcible <hi>Argument</hi> to prove and confirm their <hi>Opinion.</hi> The <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> indeed be allowed, and are of important and neceſſary uſe for the Conduct of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> in the ways of <hi>Religion:</hi> But then ſhall every <hi>Mechanick</hi> preſume to be an Interpreter and Judge (and think himſelf as infallible as the Pope in <hi>Cathedra</hi>) of all the abſtruſe and difficult <hi>Paſſages</hi> in <hi>Holy Writ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, what can it be but meer <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> and <hi>Deluſion</hi> in any one to pretend to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the dark Points of Scripture, (which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concern Mens Faith nor Manners) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the uſe of thoſe <hi>Means</hi> which are out of the reach of the <hi>Vulgar?</hi> They'l readily grant, that in all other <hi>Profeſſions, Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> a Man muſt be a conſiderable time, and take great pains to gain <hi>Experience</hi> ere he can be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of managing, and muſt be an approved
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49390:68"/>
                  <hi>Artiſt</hi> before any one will entruſt him with Buſineſs in his way of Dealings in the World. Shall every <hi>Novice</hi> then who can ſcarce read a Chapter diſtinctly in the <hi>Bible,</hi> preſume to have as much Skill in <hi>Divinity</hi> and the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> as he that has been train'd up all his life in the <hi>Schools</hi> of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> has the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vantage of all uſeful <hi>Books,</hi> underſtands the <hi>Languages</hi> wherein the <hi>Scriptures</hi> were <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally written,</hi> and makes this <hi>Study</hi> his whole <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion?</hi> Theſe are ſuch wild and extravagant <hi>Conceits,</hi> as one would think that no Man of common Reaſon and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould once pretend to: And yet there are ſeveral illiterate country <hi>Hobs,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> in Market Towns (and of my acquaintance, as there are in moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Kingdom,) who'l undertake to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and preach (according to their way; and yet) with more boldneſs and confidence than the greateſt Doctors of the <hi>Chair.</hi> But we leave ſuch to their own Fancies and Deluſions, which can neither concern you nor me more at preſent, than to pity and pray for them, that they may come in due time to a true ſenſe of their unaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Errors, and (whilſt unretracted) unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Miſtakes.</p>
               <p>Theſe I am perſuaded are ſuch <hi>Reaſons,</hi> as will puzzle our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> to anſwer, and obviate all their <hi>Pleay</hi> and <hi>Pretences</hi> to a warrantable <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> However (Sir) ſuch as they are, are
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49390:69"/>humbly offer'd to your ſerious Peruſal; and probably they may be uſeful to you in your preſent Circumſtances, having calculated them primarily for that <hi>Meridian.</hi> Yet let not theſe or any other ſo bind you up, as to neglect greater and better of your own: For it will be your great Intereſt and Advantage to weigh and meaſure the Drift and Deſign of all <hi>Counſels,</hi> by the Dictates of your own Reaſon and Judgment.</p>
               <p>I doubt I have wearied your Patience with a tedious <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> the <hi>Subjects</hi> being ſo copious have drawn it out to an undue <hi>Proportion.</hi> Yet, when you have ſeriouſly conſider'd the <hi>Scope</hi> and <hi>Deſign</hi> of it in its full Latitude and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, I hope you'l candidly excuſe not only the <hi>Length,</hi> but all other <hi>Miſtakes</hi> and <hi>Defects</hi> in it without any further Apology. Whatever <hi>Indiſcretions</hi> I have been guilty of either in the Undertaking, or management and compoſure of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> are wholly imputable to my <hi>Self;</hi> none of your <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> or <hi>Friends</hi> being yet acquainted with it. For all which I do moſt earneſtly and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg your Pardon. Now, that <hi>God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> may ever bleſs, preſerve, ſucceed, and proſper you in your Progreſs and Return; and that all your <hi>Endeavours</hi> may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Him, well-pleaſing to your Friends, and a comfort and benefit to your Self, ſhall be the moſt earneſt, hearty, and conſtant Prayer of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Prayer of, <hi>Honoured SIR,</hi>
                  </salute>
                  <signed>Your humble devoted Servant.</signed>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March 6h. Stylo vetere</hi> 1687/8.</date>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:49390:69"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
